The Grand Tour
字幕组
官方原版翻译
字幕翻译: 腐哥
创意监督: 朝思
《伟大的旅程》呈现
校对: OckRAZOR喀喀  卡卡  17  石佛哥  清野
特效: InX
压制: InX
沙漠作业
大家好 欢迎收看《伟大的旅程》
Hello, and welcome to The Grand Tour,
Sterrato在意大利语中指泥土
这是一辆兰博基尼飓风Sterrato
and this, the Lamborghini Huracán Sterrato.
与普通版不同 这辆车的设计初衷
Unlike the normal Huracán, which was designed
不是为了在市中心的深夜里 缓缓驶过招摇过市
to prowl round city centres late at night doing nine miles an hour,
而是旨在以极速横穿沙漠
this was designed to blast across a desert doing a hundred and sixty.
这款车配备了车顶架 轮拱加宽了
It's got the roof racks, it's got the flared wheel arches,
底盘加强了护板 悬挂行程也加长了
it's got beefed-up undersides, long-travel suspension.
它就是兰博基尼的痞子英雄
It is the Lamborghini 'Rogue Hero'.
进入沙漠拉力细分市场的不是只有兰博
And it's not just Lamborghini getting in on the desert raid act.
这是保时捷911 Dakar
This, is the Porsche 911 Dakar.
搭载四轮驱动 配备车底护板
It has four-wheel drive, skid plates
离地间隙比普通911高出50毫米
and fifty millimetres more ground clearance than a regular 911.
就连摩根也跃跃欲试
Even Morgan's having a go.
没错 这是CX-T 同样像是踩在高跷上
Yup, this is the CXT and it too stands upon stilts.
它配备了可调节的拉力赛规格减震器 以及外部防滚架
It's got adjustable rally spec dampers and an external roll cage.
漂亮
Nice.
毫无疑问 这几款车都出类拔萃
All these cars are of course very tremendous,
但价格也确实不菲
but they're also very not cheap.
这辆保时捷售价17万3千英镑
The Porsche is a 173,000 pounds.
摩根售价20万4千英镑
The Morgan is 204,000
而兰博 售价25万英镑
and this is 250,000.
这引发了我们的思考
And that got us thinking.
我们能不能花更少的钱 造出一辆拉力赛车
Could we build a rally raid car for less?
少得多
A lot less.
好了 来看看我们买到的车
Let's have a look at what we've bought.
我选了这辆 玛莎拉蒂GranCabrio
I went for this, a Maserati GranCabrio,
价格略低于2万6千英镑
for which I paid just under 26,000 pounds.
理查德哈蒙德买了这台
Richard Hammond has bought this,
阿斯顿马丁DB9 V12 Volante
it's an Aston Martin DB9 V12 Volante,
价格为2万2千英镑
which cost him 22,000 pounds.
杰里米克拉克森买了这辆
And Jeremy Clarkson, this,
捷豹F-Type V6S 花了2万5千英镑
the Jaguar F-Type V6S, 25,000 pounds.
一猜就是制片人威尔曼先生发来的短信
And needless to say, we've just had a text from Mr Wilman.
念吧
Go on.
他说 你们需要把买来的车改装为沙漠赛车
It says, "You will now turn your purchases into desert racers.
改装完毕后
When you finish,
前往位于毛里塔尼亚的
you will report to the railway station in the town of Choum,
舒姆镇火车站报到
which is in Mauritania."
-毛里塔尼亚在哪里 -也许他把 毛里求斯 拼错了
Where's Mauritania? Perhaps he's misspelt Mauritius?
哪儿都不是 这是一个虚构的地方
Well, it isn't anywhere. It's not a real place.
-毛里塔尼亚 -你到底是什么意思
-Well, Mauritania. -What are you on about?
拜托
Come on.
《狮子 女巫与"镜"》
"The Lion, the Witch, and the Looking Glass,"
此处哈蒙德将C.S.刘易斯作品中《爱丽丝镜中奇遇》和《纳尼亚传奇》的名字和剧情搞混了
《爱丽丝"魔衣橱"奇遇记》
"Alice Through the Wardrobe," all of that.
穿过衣橱
You go through the back of the wardrobe,
会遇到会说话的狮子
you say a cheery hello to the talking lion as you pass in,
以及穿着扑克牌图案背心四处乱跑的人
and you watch out for the people running about with playing cards on as tabards.
你说的都是C.S.刘易斯著作里的剧情
You've got C.S. Lewis echoing around in there.
-没错 -刘易斯卡洛尔
-Yes. -Lewis Carroll.
那些都不是旅行指南
They were not travel books.
你觉得这个地方根本不存在吗
You don't think this place exists?
没有毛里塔尼亚这个地方
There's no such place as Mauritania!
然而事实证明哈蒙德说错了
It turns out, however, there is such a place as Mauritania.
毛里塔尼亚位于西非 是一个前法国殖民地
It's a former French colony in West Africa.
景色是这样的
And this is what it looks like.
这个国家的面积比英国大四倍
Two thirds of this vast country, it's four times bigger than the UK,
其中三分之二的土地被撒哈拉沙漠所覆盖
has been buried...by the Sahara Desert.
这意味着在大多数情况下 沿途都是
Which means that for the most part, it is mile after mile
毫无人烟的空旷之地
of nothing... and nobody.
但在这片巨大炙热的
But here, in the middle of this gigantic sea
空旷之地的中央
of super-heated emptiness,
确实有一条铁路
there is a railway line,
这条铁路也确实穿过了
and it does pass through the small town
威尔曼先生让我们汇合的小镇
we've been told to report to...
舒姆 人口2735
温度
46摄氏度
我听说毛里塔尼亚的物价很低
I'm told you get a lot more for your money in Mauritania.
我以为这里动物会说话之类的
I thought it'd be more colourful, with talking animals.
这里很漂亮也很安静
It's nice and quiet.
是啊
Yeah.
天气太热了 都不好发出声
It's too hot to make any noise.
确实很热 46度
It's really hot. 46 degrees.
但这里是干热
It's a dry heat though.
别说...我讨厌那个词
Don't say, I hate that.
就是单纯的热
It's just hot!
-那里有一家餐厅 -哪里
-Ooh there's a restaurant. -Where?
哦对了 我们买不到啤酒
Let's get a... Oh, we can't get a beer.
-什么 -这个国家禁酒
-What? -Dry country.
-什么 -毛里塔尼亚禁酒
-What? -Mauritania's dry.
-真的吗 -这是穆斯林国家
-Seriously? -It's Muslim.
究竟什么样的童话世界 不供应金酒呢
What kind of fairy-tale land doesn't serve gin?
我倒是带了一些含酒精的洗手液
I do have some mildly alcoholic hand sanitiser, if that's any good.
务必妥善保管
Keep hold of that.
我只想说 能够再次拍摄真正意义上的《伟大的旅程》
Can I just say how nice it is to be back doing The Grand Tour,
-感觉真好 -是啊
-proper Grand Tour. -Yeah.
-你们懂我的意思吗 -懂
-Know what I mean? -Yeah.
可以来到这种尘土飞扬的世外国度
Somewhere dusty and in this case, imaginary.
他是来修理这辆货车的车身吗
Is this man coming to do some panel beating on this van?
我知道是怎么回事了
I know what this is.
这是一辆货车 是一辆非常破旧的货车
It's a van. It's a really old broken van.
我们出发之前 威尔曼先生说过
Mr Wilman said before we left...
他说 我提供了一辆备用车 以防你们谁的车出了故障
He said, "I've provided a backup vehicle for if one of your cars goes wrong."
他为什么要派一辆货车过来
Why has he sent a van?
他说我们这次旅途所需的一切
And he says everything we need for this trip
全在货车里 噢 车没锁
is in the back of the van. Oh, it's open.
你确定吗 不是在偷别人谋生的工具吧
You are sure? You're not just nicking somebody's livelihood?
确定 因为他说过
Nope. No, he said. He said.
话说你们觉得我们的车...
But it does beg the question, how do you suppose our cars are gonna get...
他说过会帮我们把车送来
He said he'd deliver them for us.
这辆货车显然是在当地买的
The van had plainly been bought locally
而我们是坐飞机来的
and we'd arrived by air,
因此哈蒙德认为 有且仅有一种可能的答案
so Hammond reckoned there could only be one possible answer.
所以你认为 我们的车会被一列火车运来吗
So you think a train is going to come along here with our cars on it?
此情此景 很可能看到火车 不是吗
Well, a train... This is a likely spot to see a train, isn't it?
-是的 这我同意 -没错
Yes, I'll grant you that. Yes.
进出的唯一途径就是火车
The only way in and out is train.
不然还怎么送呢
How else are they gonna get here?
由于没有列车时刻表
As there were no automated departure boards
告诉我们火车何时抵达
to tell us when a train might arrive,
我们只好安心等待
we settled down for the wait.
你们看到这里有多少
Have you seen how many empty plastic bottles
空的塑料瓶了吗
of water there are here?
有很多
Many.
你们看 一 二 三 四 五 六个
Look, one... I mean, two, three, four, five, six,
-七 八个 光是那边 九个 十个 -是的
-seven, eight, just there, nine, ten. -Yeah.
我要找到制造商 非杀了他们不可
I would find the manufacturers and simply kill them.
确实很糟 这些瓶子会在这里待很久
It's harsh, but it is a mess and they're going to be here for a long time.
-全是垃圾 -永远留在这里
-It's a waste. -Forever
直接在铁轨旁边等火车
It's not often you get to wait for a train
-并不常见吧 -确实不
just by the tracks, is it? -No.
-在帕丁顿火车站就不能这样 -没错
-You couldn't do this in Paddington. -No.
如果火车不来怎么办
What if it doesn't come?
如果车没在火车上怎么办
What if our cars aren't on it?
-那里 -哪里
-There. -Where?
那里 就是那列火车 肯定就是它了
There. That's it. That's gotta be it.
你说得对
Yes, you're right.
天啊 这么长
God, it's enormous!
这是我见过的最大的玩意了
That is the biggest thing I've ever seen!
也是我见过最大的
It is the biggest thing I've ever seen.
-能看到车吗 -看不到
-Can you see cars? -No.
我足够高 能看到里面是铁矿石
I'm tall enough to see iron ore.
全是铁矿石
Iron ore, iron ore.
-那是什么 -人
-What's that? -People.
伙计们 那是守车
Chaps, that is the guard's van.
-那是最后一节车厢了 -是的 但你看它前面
-That is the end. -Look what's in front...
-什么 守车前面吗 -没错 快看
-In front of the guard's van? -Yes. Look. Look,
那是一节平板车厢 是不同类型的车厢
that's a flatbed one, that's a different type of carriage.
上边放着三样东西
There's three things on it.
耶
Yeah!
这就是我们的车了
They are the cars.
火车慢慢停了下来
The train came to a halt,
我们估计它不会停很久
and as we assumed it would be setting off again quite soon,
所以要赶紧把车卸下来
we had to work quickly to get our cars off.
该怎么办 我毫无头绪
So what do you do? I've no clue.
通常而言 比如在霍恩比铁路上
What normally happens with cars on a flatbed like this,
会把平板车厢开到旁轨 放上斜坡
on a Hornby railway, is you put it in a siding with a ramp
-然后车从斜坡开下来 -没错
and then you drive them onto the ramp and down.
-但这节车厢后边有守车 -是的
But they've got the guard's van behind. Yes.
有守车 不可能直接卸车
He's not gonna set off without his guard's van, is he?
但我们可以把这两节车厢一起向后推
No, so that all goes, presumably back to-There must be a turn there.
-怎么推 -肯定有调车机车
-We can't push it. -There'll be a shunter.
这就是一个全尺寸的列车组
This is basically a full-sized train set.
另一条铁轨上肯定有调车机车 铁路都是这样
There'll be a shunter on the other line, that's how railways work.
找到调车机车后
Having found a shunter train,
詹姆斯尽他所能用法语和司机交谈
James spoke to its driver in his best French.
晚上好(意大利语) #￥%…&*…@~?
"Buona sera. Passo il oh il to oh shuntero?"
听着像是...
That sounds a bit...
可能是詹姆斯和调车机车来了
That could be James coming with a shunting engine, fully erect.
如果让他驾驶 他肯定乐坏了
If he's driving it, yeah, he'll have blown the engine.
光是登上机车就能让他嗨起来
If he's on it, he will be more aroused.
调车机车
Shunting engine.
-他在上面 -伙计们 我在调车机车上
-He's on it! -I'm on the shunter!
刚刚经过的 绝对是一个"鸡"动不已的老男人
Properly three-legged old man went past.
太爽了
Oh yes!
难道这突然成了 詹姆斯梅这辈子最美好的一天了
Is this the best day of James May's life all of a sudden?
-这就是他的游乐场 -对他来说就是全尺寸玩具
-He's got an entire railway network. -Actual full-sized train set.
如果你拥有过霍恩比列车组模型
If you've ever had a Hornby train set
那你肯定会清楚它的原理
you'll know exactly how this works. There we go.
他来了 他来了
Oh, here he comes, here he comes.
这时来了一名工作人员 轮到我炫法语了
With a train worker approaching, it was now my turn to roll out the French.
先生
Monsieur.
-谢谢 -您...您...
-Merci. -Vous vous...
我想要...您...
Je voudrais vous
让您...
you to...
解开
uncouple.
与此同时 詹姆斯也过来了
And meanwhile, here comes James.
我就是来看看你们在搞什么...
I was coming to see which bit you were...
他是世界上最快乐的人
I've never seen anybody happier.
噢噢 要动了 快上快上
Oh, he's going. Go on, get on it.
-快逃 -好可怕
-Run away! -Horror!
-一档是吧 -对对 -走起
One. -One, one, one. -Here we go.
詹姆斯亲自驾驶着调车机车
At the wheel of his big blue shunter engine,
将我们的车厢和守车推入旁轨
James pushed our cars and the guard's van into a siding,
卸下了平板车厢...
detached the car wagon...
向前推 松开刹车
So now, forwards. Release brake.
然后将守车重新接回火车上
...and then reattached the guard's van to the train,
火车搭载了更多乘客之后 再度启程
which, having taken on more passengers, set off again.
再见
Au revoir.
再见了朋友们
Au revoir, mes amis.
夕阳西下 我们要抓紧时间卸车
With the sun setting, we then had to get our cars off the wagon.
这需要用到站里一辆破旧不堪的叉车
Which meant firing up the station's extremely old and broken telehandler
以及我的农场技能
and deploying my farming skills.
再来一点点 停
Tiny bit more... stop.
这是不是我们第一次 尝试做成了一件事
Is this the first time we've ever tried to do something properly?
我们还没做成呢
We haven't done it yet.
再来一点点 好了
Tiny bit more. That's it.
然后我开始卸另外两辆车
I then set about retrieving the other two.
詹姆斯 我觉得你的车可能比我的重
I think your car might be heavier than mine, James.
-往下放 往下 -安全
Down you go. Down.
告诉我什么时候好
Tell me when I'm clear.
-我觉得可以了 -可以了
-I think you're all right. -That'll do.
嘿 我们搞定了
We've done it.
我们成功把三辆车带到毛里塔尼亚了
We've got all three cars into Mauritania.
第二天早上 经过短暂炎热且没有酒水的睡眠后
The next morning, after a short and hot, drink-free sleep,
我们相聚在一起 检查车辆的改装
we assembled to examine our modifications.
先说说我的捷豹F-Type
Starting with my Jaguar F-Type.
老实说 我有点失望
I'm a bit disappointed if I'm honest.
跟我想象的不太一样
It hasn't worked out quite how I imagined.
你想象的是什么
What did you imagine?
就是上世纪70 80年代的小孩们...
Well, you know in the 70s and 80s, -kids,
-也就是我们... -我们 对
when I say kids... us. -Us. Yeah.
你会为自己的福特Escort买宽轮拱
You'd buy flared wheel arches for your Escort
但却发现自己没钱买足够大的车轮填满轮拱
and then you couldn't afford to buy big enough wheels to fill them.
是的 就是这种离谱的外观
Yes, net result it looks ridiculous.
然后绕到这辆车后面
When you come round the back...
看上去有5米宽
It's roughly 18-feet-wide at the back.
如果我没有费心去换轮拱的话...
If I hadn't have bothered with the wheel ar...
如果你没打算换更大的轮胎
Why put the wheel arches on?
就不要装这样的轮拱
You haven't got wheels to fill them.
但是 暂且不谈这些 这还是一辆"捷捷捷捷豹"
Despite everything, it's still a "Jaaaag".
确实是"捷捷捷捷豹"
It actually says "Jaaaag".
我把车标也改了
I've changed the badge.
不 你改的是"车车车车标"
You've changed the "baaaadge".
然后我在引擎盖上装了犀鸟嘴一样的凸起
And then I've got the hornbill on the bonnet
-因为我加高了空气过滤器 -好的
coz I've lifted the air filters up. Yeah.
我还加装了Stratos灯组
Then I've gone for the Stratos light pack.
你这是在忙着为自家的丑孩子找补吧
You're busy explaining your ugly baby, aren't you?
这些讲究的是个美学
These are aesthetics.
没错 说起美学 哈蒙德
Yes, and when it comes to aesthetics, Hammond,
你是最危险的一个
you're on very, very thin ice.
-说实话 确实是 -慢着
-You are actually. -Hold on a moment.
别来那套 这就是一辆伦敦出租车
No, there is no 'hold on a moment', you've brought a Metro cab.
-你们想知道这是什么车吗 -是一辆被糟蹋了的阿斯顿马丁DB9
Do you wanna know what it is? It's an Aston Martin DB9, ruined.
你应该称呼它为"被糟蹋号"
'The Ruined' is what you should call it.
我的车只是轻度损坏 你的完全被糟蹋了
Mine is mildly spoiled, yours is totally ruined.
我不要听废话 最重要的是
Noise, noise, noise. Headlines:
这是一辆可以住进去的阿斯顿马丁
it's an Aston Martin you can live in.
这是一顶帐篷 展开就是一座房子
That is a tent, it folds out, it's a house.
我住在阿斯顿马丁街1号
I live at number 1, Aston Martin Street.
-这是顶帐篷 -是的
-That's a tent? -That's a tent.
太漂亮了 像鲨鱼一样 看起来很隐秘
This is beautiful, it looks like a shark, it looks stealthy.
不好意思...
Sorry...
它充满了潜力 而这种潜力就是能住进去
It's filled with potential and that potential is to live in it.
你为什么要给它装上 碳纤维的"双胸"
And why have you given it carbon fibre breasts?
因为我抬高了前面的进气口
Because I've raised the air intakes at the front.
-和我那犀鸟装饰是一个道理 -是的
Oh, so it's the same as my hornbill arrangement.
这就是它的作用 而且我抬高了悬挂系统
Yeah, so that's what that's doing. And then I've raised the suspension.
-你还准备了照明设备 -够了
-You've got your lighting rig. -That's enough.
我们去看看我的车吧
We will go and look at my car...
我不想讨论你的车
I don't want to talk about your car.
-不 你肯定想 在这边 -不 我不想
-No, you do. -No I don't. -This way.
好样的 詹姆斯 毫无疑问 这辆车相当漂亮
Well done, James, that is unquestionably
-比原版更漂亮 -确实
-a good-looking car.  -It does.
-你甚至还给它加上了漂亮的条纹 -没错
-You've even put nice stripes on it. -I have.
我一直不喜欢这款车的外观
I've never liked the look of this car.
但现在不一样了
But now you do.
外观确实改进了
That actually is improved.
你的...空气过滤器是怎么装的
Where's your-How have you got your air filters up?
其实这不是原厂引擎盖
Actually the bonnet is different.
它的灵感来源是MC12引擎盖
This is a sort of facsimile of the MC bonnet
如果你们还记得那款巨大的中置引擎超跑
if you remember the gigantic mid-engine supercar
加装了额外的通风口 而且这里还有一个槽
and it has extra vents in it and it has a slot there.
这就像圣诞节的早晨 你收到的礼物比我的好 我不开心
This is like Christmas morning and you got a better present than me. I don't feel very good.
描述得非常准确
It's exactly what it is.
你的车比我的车好看 我太不爽了
I'm so cross that your car looks better than my car.
当然比你的好看了
Well, of course it does.
看起来简直跟我的车一样帅气
It looks damn near as good as mine.
防滚架又是怎么回事
And what's with the roll cage?
以防车辆翻滚
In case it rolls over.
所以...等一下
Oh, hang on.
啊哈
Aha!
来了
Here it is...
-短信 -威尔曼先生发来的短信
-Text. -Text from Mr Wilman
你们以前曾经开车穿越过沙漠
"You have driven across deserts in the past,
但今天要面对的是大沙漠
but this is the big one,
这里是世界上最大的撒哈拉沙漠
"this is the Sahara, the biggest desert in the world.
现在你们将开车穿越撒哈拉沙漠
"And you will now drive across it for a thousand miles
行程1600公里 直抵塞内加尔的海滩
"to the beach in Senegal
那里曾经是 巴黎达喀尔拉力赛的终点
where the Paris-Dakar used to finish."
等一下 我们是要重走巴黎达喀尔拉力赛的路线吗
Wait a minute, we are doing the Paris-Dakar?
这简直就是梦想成真
We are-This is boy's own dream.
更好的消息是
It's actually better than that,
我们不用跑从巴黎出发的无聊路段
because we don't have to do the boring bit from Paris, we're just doing...
只有最刺激的沙漠赛段
The deserty exciting bits you want to do.
-巴黎达喀尔拉力赛的精华 太棒了-最好的一段
-The best bits of the Paris-Dakar. -That's quite epic. -That is legend.
先生们 继续听
Gentlemen, gentlemen.
短信后半短可能说明了 为什么巴黎达喀尔拉力赛
This might have something to do with why the Paris-Dakar no longer happens in this part of the world,
被迫换地方
because there's more.
你们目前处于外交部认定的危险地区
"You are currently in a Foreign Office red zone.
政府表示不排除该地区有恐怖主义风险
"The government says terrorism cannot be ruled out
此外 在西撒哈拉边界之外
"and over the border in Western Sahara, there's a small war going on
独立主义分子正与摩洛哥武装力量交战
"between separatists and the Moroccans.
我们甚至不得不事先通知摩洛哥国防部
"We've even had to warn the Moroccan Defence Ministry
告知其我们正在该地区活动 以防其将我们的摄制组车队
"about our presence here in case they think our crew vehicles
误认为是武装力量 从而发起攻击
are an assault force and attack,
所以你们规矩一点
"so behave yourselves."
随着警告声在耳畔不断回响 我们发动了引擎
With that warning ringing in our ears, we fired up our engines...
要想前往达喀尔
...and knowing only that to get to Dakar,
我们只能一路向西南方向行驶
we had to keep heading south-west,
深入撒哈拉沙漠
plunged into the Sahara.
开着450匹马力的阿斯顿马丁参加达喀尔拉力赛
450 horsepower, doing the Dakar in an Aston.
虽然哈蒙德热情高涨
Despite Hammond's enthusiasm,
但毫无疑问 这项任务对我们的车来说是个艰巨的挑战
there was no doubt that our cars faced a daunting task.
因为这些车的设计初衷 并不是为了参加拉力赛
Because they really hadn't been conceived to do this kind of thing.
相当于我们带着稍加改造的超模 参加自由搏击锦标赛
We've brought lightly modified supermodels to a kickboxing championship.
我这辆车其实立项于
Thing about my car is, it actually started life
玛莎拉蒂属于法拉利的时期
when Maserati was part of Ferrari,
但开发进程过半时
but then halfway through its development,
拥有整个集团的菲亚特决定
Fiat, who owned the whole lot,
将玛莎拉蒂并入阿尔法罗密欧
decided that Maserati should be part of Alfa Romeo.
因此 玛莎拉蒂重新开始 用经过改造的总裁轿车制造了这款车
So Maserati started again and used a chopped-up Quattroporte to make this.
F-Type有点大杂烩的味道
The F-Type was a bit of a hotchpotch.
最早是在XJ的基础上
It started out in life as an XJ saloon
削减制造出了XK
and then they cut it down to make the XK,
又经过再次削减  造出了F-Type
then they cut it down again to make the F-Type,
所以这辆车实际上是经历过两次削减
so it's really a cut and shut of a cut and shut.
引擎的设计也相当混乱复杂
The engine's a bit of a mangled up mishmash as well
他们原本想要一台V6 但又没钱自己研发
because they wanted a V6 but couldn't afford to develop their own,
所以只好找来一台V8 砍掉两个缸
so they got their V8 and just chopped two cylinders off it.
这不就是V6嘛
And there we are, V6.
能用 说实话 确实能用
It works! And I've gotta be honest, it does.
特别是带机械增压的 你听
Especially with a super charger, which you can hear.
我这辆的外观设计 实际上诞生于捷豹的设计中心
My car was actually styled at Jaguar's design centre
是真的 在他们办公室一角的幕布后面设计的
in a corner of the office behind a curtain, genuinely.
然后用大量的福特零件组装而成
And then it was put together using quite a lot of Ford-based parts.
但它仍然是一辆阿斯顿马丁
But it is still an Aston Martin,
很多人认为 这辆车是从旧DB时代算起
and many feel it's the first proper Aston Martin
第一辆纯血马丁
since the old DB days.
导航睡醒了
Oh, sat-nav's woken up.
"显然"我们目前位于曼彻斯特南部
Just south of Manchester, apparently.
快看这个 沙丘
Ooh, look at this. Dunes!
妥妥的撒哈拉
Proper Sahara.
沙丘是出了名的危险
Dunes are notoriously dangerous.
所以我们决定做点傻事
So we decided to muck about.
我们可不是痞子英雄 我们是夺金三王
Oh, yeah. We are not the rogue heroes. We are the three kings.
多亏了我的USB连接
And thanks to my USB connectivity,
我们有原声带可听
we have a soundtrack.
Chicago - If you leave me now
♪ If you leave me now ♪
♪You'll take away the biggest part of me ♪
♪ Ooh, no, baby, please don't go ♪
♪ And if you leave me now ♪
♪ You'll take away the very heart of me ♪
♪ Ooh, no, baby, please don't go ♪
♪ Ooh, girl, I just want you to stay ♪
妈的
Oh, f-ing hell!
不要切弯走捷径
Ah, don't cut the corners.
千万要记住
There's a top tip there.
不好了
Oh no. Oh no.
我觉得我的空调刚刚坏了
I think my air-conditioning just packed up.
我真觉得坏了
I genuinely think it did.
你这运气真是差到难以置信
That is an unbelievably rotten bit of luck.
我的还能用
Mine's working.
外面的温度是多少
What is the temperature out there?
48度 我的天啊
48 degrees. Holy cow.
发动机温度过高 请立即停车
High engine temp. Stop.
我的车让我立即停车
Mine is telling me to stop immediately.
我的天啊
Good God.
嗨
Hi.
啊
Ah.
请问 先生您遇到了什么问题
What seems to be the trouble, sir?
-遇到了什么麻烦 -看这里就知道了
-Having a spot of bother, are we? -A lot of it can be explained by that.
原来如此
Oh, yes.
-你拿的什么 -风扇
-What have you got there? -A fan.
彼特·琼斯: BBC商业投资真人秀《龙穴》常驻评委
-好吧 -从彼特琼斯那儿买的
Right. From Peter Jones.
空调刚才真的坏了
It really has stopped working in there.
我在想是不是皮带掉了
That's what I'm wondering, if it's lost the belt.
-这是什么 -我怀疑是冷却液
-What's that? -That's coolant, I suspect,
可能是这里流出来的
that's probably come out of here.
奇怪的是 阿斯顿马丁自称是手工打造的
And it's weird, cos it says it's handbuilt.
没错 说明安装过程非常仔细
-Yeah, I think... -Which means done really carefully.
英国纯手工打造
"Handbuilt in England."
问题出在这里
That's the problem.
找到原因了
There it is.
-依然异常 -你什么都没修啊
-It's still off the dial. -You can't just sit there. You're going to have to get...
我得让它冷却一下 什么都不能碰
I'm going to have to let it cool, that's all I can do. I can't touch anything.
-你得修好啊 -为什么不能碰
-You've got to mend it. -Why can't you touch it?
因为非常烫
Because it's hot.
所以你打算等凉下来了再修
So you wait for it to cool down, then take the engine out.
不可能啊 环境温度都49
It'll never cool down. It's 49 degrees.
仪表已经爆表了
It's right at the top of the gauge.
不是 我是说外部温度
No, no, no. External temperature.
63度
63.
-什么单位 华氏吗 -华氏度 -不可能是60华氏度
-What, that's Fahrenheit? -Fahrenheit, yes. -Well, it's not 60. -That's a summer's...
这辆车还以为我们在诺丁汉
This thinks it's in Nottingham.
别笑 你看嘛
It does, look.
华氏度63 定位在诺丁汉
It's 63 degrees Fahrenheit and it's in Nottingham.
这车就是这么认为的
That's what it thinks.
所以 我们该怎么办
So, what are we going to do?
鉴于哈蒙德有房有车
Given that Hammond had a house and a car
而且他的车以为自己身处东米德兰 沐浴着春光
which believed it was in the East Midlands on a nice spring day,
所以我决定不把电风扇给他
I decided not to give him my fan.
然后转身离开
And then we left.
情况简报 我们已经出发了15分钟
OK, sitrep. We've done 15 minutes of travel
只有两辆车正常行驶
and two of us are still moving.
幸运的是 我很快找到了问题所在
Mercifully, I worked out what was wrong quite quickly.
我之前以为这些液体是冷却液
This fluid that I thought was coolant from the engine
它们沸腾后溢出
that had boiled over and come out
但其实不是冷却液
isn't engine coolant.
而是转向助力油 是从这里流出来的
It's power steering fluid. It's come out of there.
沸腾的原因是发动机舱里太热了
That just got hot and boiled because it was so hot in the engine bay.
我急需散热
I need to get heat out.
对了 威尔曼先生的备用货车
Right, Mr Wilman's backup van.
里面肯定有工具
There must be tools.
开玩笑吗 我希望用不到这个
Really? God, I hope I don't need that.
慢着 这个行吗
Oh, hang on. Tools?
好了
Right.
这样做让我很痛苦 撬在你身 伤在我心
Oh. Oh, that's causing me pain. It hurts me more than you.
好了
There.
一定要启动啊
Please start.
太好了 给足了你空气
Yes. And I've given you air.
还有一件事我可以做 帮助冷却发动机
There was one other thing I could do to help cool the engine,
但其痛苦程度难以想象
but it was unimaginable.
我不想这样做 但我不得不
I don't want to do it. I'm going to have to do it.
把暖风调大
Turn the heating up,
因为这样一来 会把发动机舱下的热空气吸出来
because that will actually pull hot air out from under the engine bay
送到我这里
and deliver it to me.
现在热起来了
Oh, yeah, that is hot now.
镜头转向前方
Up ahead,
这里指Top Gear北极特辑
上一次如此孤独 还是和詹姆斯在北极
I hadn't felt this alone since James and I drove to the North Pole.
毛里塔尼亚空无一人
Mauritania is empty.
入眼之处 尽是荒芜
Totally empty. Look at it.
荒无人烟
No one comes here.
当我们拿到拍摄许可证时 许可证编号是58
When we got the filming permit, it was number 58.
这是毛里塔尼亚自1960年以来
The 58th filming permit
签发的第58张拍摄许可证
this country has issued since 1960.
那可是63年啊
That's 63 years.
这么长时间 只签发了58张拍摄许可证
They've only issued 58 filming permits.
哈蒙德 你回来了
Hammond, you're back.
我在引擎盖上打了孔 开着暖风在跑
Made holes in the bonnet and I'm running with the heater on.
我命不久矣
I don't have long to live.
那可不怎么样
Ooh, I don't fancy that.
我们带着"自热锅"同事继续前行
We continued onwards with our boil-in-the-bag colleague
直到三台口渴的引擎需要加油
until our thirsty engines needed petrol.
由于撒哈拉没多少加油站
Which, because the Sahara doesn't have many service stations,
我们只能靠威尔曼先生提供的加油车了
meant pulling over at a fuel bowser that Mr Wilman had provided.
你怎么已经湿成这个样子了
How have you got yourself in that state?
因为出汗 我们都有了安全带的印子
We got... we got seatbelt marks.
-我可是在蒸锅里啊 -天啊
-I'm in an Aga. Literally an Aga. -Oh dear.
我能跟你俩说句话吗
Can I just have a word with you two?
什么
What?
说什么
伙计们 我们出发之前
Chaps, before we set off, Mr Wilman said,
威尔曼先生问我能否...
could we stage a,
能否人为上演一出事故
let's be honest, contrived accident? Yeah.
让油罐车爆炸
Where the fuel tanker blows up.
什么
The what?
他想让我们演那种"噢不 我们被困沙漠 没油了"的惊恐
Because he'll want us to have "oh, no, we're stuck in the desert "with no fuel" panics.
-对 电视上的经典桥段 -没错
-TV jeopardy. -There you go.
不 不是
No, no, no, no, no.
他想在预告片里放一组爆炸的镜头
He wants an explosion to put in the trailer of the show.
-好吧 -我不同意
-Oh, right. -I'd vote no to that.
-我也不同意 -我也是
-I would as well. -I'd vote no.
-扯淡 -不 我不想炸飞它
-That's cheese. -I don't want to blow it up.
-但他想让我们这么做 -好吧
-Plus he wants us to. -Right.
所以我们要用生命保护这辆车
So let's look after this with our lives.
这是我们最宝贵的东西了
It's the most precious thing we have.
好的 我加满了 梅
Right, I'm full. May?
-怎么了 -轮到你加了
-Yes? -She's all yours.
詹姆斯 你要去哪里
James, where are you going?
我正在量长度 这样就可以把它绕到车这里
I'm getting a length on so we can get it round here.
你们能不能按一下按钮...
Could you press the button to, um,
-就在那下面 有一个... -好的 找到了
-it's down there? It's got a little... -Oh, yeah, got it.
-对 就是那里 -有一个油箱盖开关
-Yeah, it's there. -It's there. -We can see that. -It's got a petrol pump on...
-能按一下吗 -我们看到了
-Can you press it? -Yeah.
-是的 还要别的吗 -是的 你能按一下吗
-Anything else? -Yeah, can you press it?
-可以 我...然后... -能麻烦您按一下吗
-Uh, I, yeah, I, I... -Would you press it, please?
-我按了 -他确实按过了
-I've done it. -He did press it.
-你没按 -他按了
-He didn't. -He did.
我真的按了
Apart from I did.
-你没按 -我刚又按了一次
-You didn't. -I just pressed it again.
请打开点火开关 再按一下 好吗
Could you turn the ignition on and press it, please?
这可是两件事啊
Oh, that means two things.
行了
There you go.
你刚才说得可真清楚
So, they're really good instructions.
我警告过你 詹姆斯 油枪可烫了
I warned you, James. It's the hottest thing in the...
从炙手可热的加油车那里加满油后 我们继续前进
Having filled up from the very toasty fuel bowser, we moved on.
很快 我们就遇到了第一个重大的地形问题
And pretty soon, we encountered our first big geological problem.
伙计们 我有点不安
Chaps, I'm a little bit unnerved by that...
眼前的峭壁无边无际
endless cliff face in front of us.
根本看不到尽头
I mean, there is no end in sight.
那座山脉一眼望不到尽头
There is no end in sight of that mountain range.
完蛋
Bugger.
既然有人费心开辟这条路
If somebody's gone to the bother of making this track,
为什么不开辟一条 通往悬崖底部的路呢
they wouldn't just build a track to the bottom of the cliff, would they?
很快 我们就明白为什么会有路了
Soon, we found out why there was a track.
为什么会有人在撒哈拉沙漠的中部
Why the bloody hell would somebody build a tunnel
修建一条隧道呢
in the middle of the Sahara Desert?
可能是某种可怕物质的矿场
Probably a mine for something scary.
-开采什么 灰尘吗 -哈蒙德 里面没什么可怕的
Mining what, though? Dust? Hammond, there'll be nothing scary in it.
嘿詹姆斯 我们可以在这里举行比赛
Hey! James, we could have a race down here.
这主意太棒了 我一点都不想参加
That's an excellent idea and I don't want to take part.
你们不觉得这是个好主意吗
Don't you think that's a good idea?
有谁在撞上...之前 达到的车速最高
Who can reach the highest speed and then brake before hitting...
哦对 你参加不了
Oh, no, you can't do that.
糟糕兄弟们 别动
Oh shit! Shit! Guys stop.
咋了
What?
有蝙蝠
They're bats.
-有很多蝙蝠 出去吧 大家伙 -我害怕蝙蝠
There's a lot of bats. Out. Out now, everybody out.
蝙蝠并不危险
Bats aren't dangerous.
蝙蝠不危险?...你以为是史酷比狗啊
Bats aren't... That's just... You're thinking of Scooby-Doo.
-你们听说过埃博拉吗 -听说过
Yes.
患病后眼睛 鼻子都会出血
You bleed from your eyes, your nose,
-身体上所有孔洞全都会出血 -是的
all your orifices,-all of them. -Yes
-然后很快就会死亡 -是的
And then you die quickly. -Yes.
但你还有足够的时间 让家人赶到你的床边
But just enough time for your family to get to your bedside
然后你就会爆炸 让家人沐浴在你被感染的血液中
and then you explode, showering them with infected blood.
大多数专家认为埃博拉病毒携带于西非的蝙蝠身上
Most experts agree it lives in bats in West Africa.
而我们就在西非
And we're in West Africa.
但我们现在有一个问题
-But we now have a problem.
-并没有 因为我们不进隧道
-Not really. We don't go in the tunnel.
不 我们必须进隧道
Well, no, we have to go in the tunnel.
我们必须进入隧道 而且必须开得非常快
We have to go in the tunnel and we have to drive incredibly quickly.
-不开快 -是的
No, not incredibly quickly.
-开快会把东西扬起来 -你刚说病毒可能会在蝙蝠粪便里
You'll kick stuff up. It could be in bat guano, did you say?
-可能会...是的... -那就是蝙蝠大便
-It could be... Yeah, nobody... -That's bat poo.
-是的 蝙蝠大便 -就在地面上
Yeah, bat poo. Which would be on the floor. Exactly.
你的车轮可能会把粪便扬起来
You'll kick it up with your wheels by going...
-会被我们吸入体内 -我们一个一个来 飞速通过
One at a time. Incredibly quickly.
好的 车窗升起
Right, windows up.
空气再循环模式 这样一来会把车内的空气
Air on recirculation so it takes the air in the cabin
送回车内循环
and sends it back into the cabin.
我不想得埃博拉
I don't want Ebola.
好的 我要开始了
Right, here I go.
很好 慢点 不要
That's good. Doucement. Doucement. No!
-埃博拉被扬起来了 -快跑
-And there's the Ebola. -Run away.
蝙蝠! 从窗外飞过!
Oh, there's a bat! A bat went past the window!
我中了埃博拉!
I've got Ebola!
这破隧道有多长
How long is this bloody thing?
哦到头了!放松放松放松
Oh, there's the end! Relax, relax, relax.
我的天啊
Oh, Christ!
这都是些啥玩意儿
What the... the bloody hell's that all about?
-准备驶入 车速一定要明智... -别把灰尘扬起来
Going in. Don't make, don't kick up -a load of dust.
我不会把灰尘扬起来的
-I'm not going to kick up dust.
天啊
Shit.
注意 危险 雷区
看来这就是与西撒哈拉之间的边界
So that's the border with Western Sahara.
哈蒙德
Hammond, Hammond, Hammond.
理查德哈蒙德 能听到吗
Richard Hammond, can you hear me?
有光了!
Oh, there's light, there's light!
-嘿 快停车 -妈的
-Stop, stop, stop! -Bloody hell!
按着车辙印原路退回
Back up exactly where your wheels are.
上面写着"地雷"
It says "mines".
没错 你身处雷区
Yes, you're in a minefield.
按着车辙印原路退回 因为这些地方没有地雷
Back up exactly where your wheels are, 'cause we know there are no mines there.
你要开车驶过铁丝网
You're going to drive over the barbed wire,
可能会给你的车穿个孔
which will probably give you a puncture,
但放轻松
but relax on that.
好了 你安全了
Right. You're safe.
-雷区 -我知道 那就是西撒哈拉
-Minefield. -I know. That is Western Sahara.
你觉得这真的是雷区吗
Do you think it really is a minefield?
这种标识 一般都会宁可信其有吧
Well, it's the kind of thing you generally take a sign's word for.
如果上边写的是 "小心 毛毛虫出没"
If it said "Caution caterpillars",
我会想进去看看
I'd go and have a look.
但是 只挂标识不埋雷 不也一样 吗
But, I mean, you only need to put the sign up, don't you?
是的 但也有可能真就埋雷了
Yeah, but you might have put the mines in as well.
没错 但换做是我 我肯定只挂个标识
Yeah, but if I were them, I'd just put the sign up.
-那是因为你很懒而且没有地雷 -是的
-You're lazy and don't have any mines. -Yes.
但我认为 那里没有地雷
No, but in my mind, there aren't any mines there.
-我们要进去慢跑一圈吗 -算了
-Shall we go for a little jog? -No.
这是什么...
What the hell is...
-那是什么 -雷区
-What's that? -It's a minefield.
-是的 -哈蒙德刚刚进去过了
-A minefield. -Hammond's been in it.
-你进去过了吗 -他冲破了栅栏
-You've been in it? -He crashed through the fence.
我们现在遇到了问题
We now had a problem.
横在我们面前的 是一个必须假定为真的雷区
In front of us was what we had to assume was an actual minefield.
挡在我们后面的 是一条充斥着有毒蝙蝠粪便的隧道
While behind us was a tunnel full of infected bat dung.
我不想重新回去穿过埃博拉隧道
I don't want to go back through the tunnel of Ebola.
而且即便我们原路返回
And even if we do go back that way
还有那巨大的悬崖
here's that massive cliff face.
没错 但那是个可以尝试克服的问题
Yes, but that's a problem to try and overcome.
是可以尝试解决的问题
That's something to try and solve.
而这不行 根本无法解决
-That isn't. You can't solve it.
是的 所以我们别无选择
-Yes, so, we have no choice.
-应该朝那边走 -你说得对 相当对
-That's navigation. -You're right. You're absolutely right.
我们别无...我们不能...
We have no... We cannot...
有雷!
Not in the minefield!
停车
Stop!
-停车 -停车
威尔曼的预告片可能有戏了
Wilman might get his trailer.
卡车爆炸的时候 你们要站在这儿不动吗
No, well, are you gonna stand here while he does?
不 我要后退
No, I'm gonna back up.
油罐车消失在了视线中 但并没有爆炸
The fuel tanker disappeared out of sight without detonating.
但这并没有改变我们的想法
But that didn't change our minds.
于是我们调转方向...
So, we turned round...
顺着隧道原路返回
...and went back through the tunnel.
我们怎么越过悬崖
How are we going to get over that?
我不知道怎么才能越过
I don't know how we're going to get over.
数小时之后 我们终于找到了一条
After many hours, we eventually found a rough track,
看起来可能通向悬崖顶部的崎岖小路
which looked like it might go to the top of the escarpment.
这一段有点坎坷
Ooh, this is bumpy, this bit.
好样的 加油啊 捷豹 你可以的
Yeah. Come on, Jag. You can do this.
这辆车让我大为惊讶
This car is actually surprising me.
我觉得可能是因为 这辆捷豹很轻 不是吗
I suppose it's 'cause it's light, isn't it, the Jag?
是啊 重量会很大程度上影响性能
Well, that makes a huge difference, yeah.
我觉得我这辆车现在有两吨多了
I think mine probably weighs more than two tonnes now.
加油啊
Come on. Oh!
该死
Oh, bloody hell!
天啊 加油啊
God, come on!
完蛋玩意儿
Bollocks.
他来了 他开着捷豹来了
Here he comes, in the Jaguar.
你会撞到那块大石头的
You're going to hit that big rock.
你瞧好了...
-Behold the-
Oooh.
你瞧好了...
-Behold the-
杰里米 如果你能轻轻推我一下 那就太好了
If you can move and give me a tiny nudge, Jezza, that would be brilliant.
小马拉了大车
The gazelle has moved the walrus.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
加油啊 慢一点 就是这样
Come on, gently. Yes, yes.
我有点爱上这辆捷豹了
I'm beginning to rather like my Jaag.
实在抱歉 我最开始对这辆车很失望
I'm sorry I was initially disappointed in it,
但现在我觉得它太棒了
Because it's bloody brilliant.
最终 我们实现了目标
Eventually, we achieved our objective.
这绝对是最高处...
Well, this is definitely the top.
要我说
I'd say.
那里看起来好像是一个建筑工地
And that appears to be a... that's a building site.
那是我们的加油车吗
Is that our fuel bowser?
它肯定穿过雷区了 不是吗
He must have got through that minefield, mustn't he?
它还没爆炸 威尔曼先生肯定会非常生气
Mr Wilman's going to be furious 'cause it hasn't blown up.
他的预告片没戏了
He's got nothing for his trailer.
好吧 伙计们 我想就此停车
Yeah, uh, chaps, I'm inclined to stop here.
为什么
Why?
你们自己看
You'll see.
看 那里有一条路
Ooh, yeah.
-还真是啊 -是的 还是条好路
Well, yeah, there is, and it is a nice road, but
-没错 -在那下面
-Exactly. -It's down there.
-但那条马路连不到这里吧 -没错 不连着
It doesn't join up with here, does it? It's not connected to here.
-我们把车从这里开下去 -什么
-We'll drive down here. -What?
-我们把车从这里开下去 -"可不嘛 沿着那条路"
Yeah, down that track.
这可是悬崖
It's a cliff.
我们站立的地方和那条路之间
There's too much gravity immediately available
可要受到不小的重力影响
between where we're standing and that road.
但重力是安全可预测的
And it isn't a cruel and unpredictable mistress.
是的 非常可靠
No, it's bloody reliable.
听我说 如果我先走
-Listen, if I go first... -Yeah.
-其实我已经准备好这么做了... -真的吗
Which I'm prepared to do... -Really?
真的 我先走
Yeah, I'll go first.
-备用货车在那儿 对吧 -对
The backup van's there, yes? Yes.
备用车里肯定有线缆
That's bound to have some cable in it.
为啥不把我的车 跟一台挖掘机连在一起呢
Why don't I attach my car to one of those diggers?
其实 我们可以 把另一台挖掘机当做滑轮
Actually, we could use the other one as a pulley.
然后我开车下去
And then I drive down,
但我有线缆确保我的安全
but I've got the safety of the cable.
你小时候肯定是把工程师和漫画家搞混淆了
Years ago, at some point, you confused engineers with cartoonists.
你这样做是非常值得赞扬的
What this is, is a very, very, very
经过精心设计的自杀行为
commendably elaborate suicide.
尽管如此 我们别无选择
Nevertheless, there was no other choice,
只能前往备用货车里翻箱倒柜
so we went for a rummage in the backup van.
这条线缆很合适
That is a proper cable.
额定载重是四五吨
Is it rated to four or five tonnes?
看起来是这样的
Looks like it.
肯定会非常沉
It'll be incredibly heavy.
-好的 准备好了吗 -小心脚
-Right, are we ready? -Feet.
开始了
Here we go.
我在没求助挖掘机驾驶员的情况下 布置好了线缆
Once I'd rigged up the cables with no help at all from the digger drivers,
给他们的老板付了钱...
and paid their boss...
"一万乌吉亚
Ten thousand MRU's.
"克拉克森勋爵"
Lord Clarkson.
恐怕我没有支票保付卡
I don't have a check guarantee card, I'm afraid,
但放心吧 我可是有捷豹的人
but it's OK, because I have a "Jaaaag".
然后我向同事们解释了 整个装置的布置
I then explained the setup to my colleagues.
-所以 我开车过去 对吗 -对
-So, I drive over there, yeah? -Yeah.
然后那台挖掘机里的小伙子 将会向前行驶
And then the chap in that digger is going to drive forwards
与我下山保持相同速度
at the same speed I'm driving down the hill.
-然后那些滑轮... -对
-And then, those pulleys. -Yes.
他可以左右摆动这支机械臂
He can swing this arm.
如果我下坡过程中需要改变方向
So, as I perhaps change direction as I go down the slope,
找出一条路时 你们需要告诉他
picking out a route, you'll need to tell him
向左或者向右摆动
to swing it right or left. So...
-他会说英语吗 -什么
-Does he speak English? -What?
-他会... -不会
-Does he... -No.
他们都是毛里塔尼亚人 但会说阿语和法语
They're all actually Mauritanian, but they speak Arabic and French.
-好的 -阿语没戏
-Arabic? No.
-法语 -法语 全靠我了
French? -French. I'm your man.
后盾搞定之后 我爬上了车
With my back-up sorted, I climbed aboard.
你要挂档下去还是空档下去
Are you going to go down in gear or in neutral?
我得开车 不是吗我得挂一档
I've got to drive, haven't I? I need to be in first.
好了 我们准备好了吗
Right, are we ready?
放心交给我们吧 我们会帮你看好的 我们支持你
Stand on us, we'll see you right. You have our support.
天啊
Jesus.
-向左 -左一点点
Little bit of left.
左一点点
Bit of left.
你很接近...你正在驶下悬崖
You're very close to the... you're driving off a cliff.
我看不...但好处是
But the good thing is,
由于我的Stratos聚光灯组 我看不到眼前
due to my Stratos spotlights,, I can't see that.
好吧
OK.
我才意识到我要怎么下去 并不喜欢这样
I can now see what I've got to do for the first time. Don't like this.
说实话 我真不喜欢这样
Actually, really don't like this.
我得向左走
I need to go left.
麻烦让他把机械臂往左挥
If you can ask him to swing his arm left.
把机械臂往左挥 马上通知
Swing his arm left. On it.
我可不想掉进那条沟壑里
'Cause I don't want to go down that gully.
（法语）请 非常
S'il vous plaît, beaucoup...
...左
left.
（法语）右
Droite.
哈蒙德 不管你刚才比划了啥 效果还不错
Whatever you mimed, Hammond, wasn't bad.
拜托 转向啊 你个混蛋
Come on, turn, turn, turn, you bastard.
好的 往左
Come left, come left.
往左啊 我的小山羊汽车
Come left, my little mountain goat of a car.
-这样好多了 -笔直向前
-That's better. -All straightened.
天啊 我在干什么
Christ, what am I doing?
到达这个位置之后 我认为剩下的路
I'd now reached a point where I reckoned I could go the rest of the way
完全可以靠我自己的动力
under my own steam.
这不是很实用的日常解决方案吧
It's not a practical, everyday kind of solution, is it?
-速度不算快 -没错
-It's not quick. -No.
-而且还得准备几台挖掘机 -是啊
-And you need a couple of spare diggers. -Yeah.
好的 我开始了
OK, here I go.
天啊 我的妈呀
Ooh, God, struth.
我在侧着走
I'm going sideways.
笔直向前
Straighten out!
好了 速度和动力
OK. Speed and power!
我上路了
I'm on a road! I'm on a road!
哈蒙德和梅 现在轮到你们了
Hammond and May, your turn now.
真的很简单 一点也不可怕
It's really easy, not frightening at all.
但是 在我们与杰里米汇合之前
Before we could join Jeremy, though, we had to make sure
我们得先确保 珍贵的重达九吨的油罐车安全驶下悬崖
that our precious nine-tonne fuel tanker got down safely.
如果你必须将一辆油罐车驶下悬崖
If you had to lower a fuel tanker down a cliff,
那么在他们两人中 你最不想让谁牵头
which two human beings would you least like to be in charge?
我们是百分之一百万的确定
Are we one million percent sure
-这样做是安全的吗 -说实话 到不了百分之一百万
this is going to be safe? Not a million percent, to be honest.
即便杰里米坐在那辆捷豹里 也没这辆油罐车重
This is heavier than the Jag, though, even with him in it.
好了 送油罐车下去吧
Right, send it down.
-不行 太多了 -太多了 回来 回来一点
Too much. Back a bit.
完球
Ballocks!
天啊
Oh dear
这声音太可怕了
That noise is horrible.
路程过半后 司机请求释放线缆
At the halfway point, the driver asked us to release the cables
这样一来 剩余的下降路线 他可以靠自己来驾驶
so he could do the rest of the drop on his own.
好吧 我知道油罐车里的那个人 是什么感觉
OK, I know what it feels like for that man in that fuel tanker.
菊花一紧
Bottom loosening.
我们必须尽力向左打方向
I think we need a bit of serious left-hand down
才能避免杰里米刚才遇到的问题
if he's going to avoid the problem that Jeremy had,
因为他不能往那个方向走太多
'cause he mustn't go too far that way.
他需要...尽快开始向左转
He needs to start going left as soon as he can.
詹姆斯 现在我们是第一次
James, now that we've moved down the hill a bit further
-往山下走了一点... -怎么了
-for the first time. -Yeah?
你看到我看到的东西了吗在那边
Have you seen what I've seen over there?
我的天啊
Oh, my God.
不好了
Oh, no.
先生们 加油车下山了
Gentlemen, the fuel bowser is down.
虽说卡住了 但确实下来了
It's stuck, but it's down.
兄弟们 好消息
Guys, good news.
它很接近山脚下了 而且好消息是不会爆炸
He's made it just about to the bottom. It's not going to blow up, which is good.
而且前保险杠掉落
And the front bumper has come off,
我觉得这一幕放在预告片里 会非常好看
which I think's going to work quite well as something in the trailer.
了不起
That's amazing.
真的...太叹为观止了
It is really really... That was proper impressive.
另一个境界 而且没爆炸 一点都没
Something else. But, I mean, it's just... And it's no explosion, nothing.
-你们怎么下来的 -我们顺着路开下来的
-How did you get down? -Oh, we came on the road.
-你是说... -没错
Are you telling me...
说实话 实在太意外了 路就在施工场地后边
I'm not going to lie. It was quite a surprise. It's behind the building site.
他们是在修路 所以有挖掘机
That's why they've got those diggers and things over there.
-他们一直在修路 -但他们修完了 一路修到了顶部
-They've been building a road. -They've just got to the top.
-修的很平整 -很不错
-It's a nice road. -It's lovely.
-人齐了 大家都很高兴 很安全 -我不高兴
We're all here. Everybody's happy. -I'm not happy.
所有的车都下来了
All the cars came down
-我坐着这个从那里下来的 那里 -是的
I came down there. I came down that, in that. Yes, well.
说实话 我们刚才很轻松 是一条新修的公路
That was pretty easy. It's a new road.
很漂亮 是沥青路面 边缘还有一点沙子
It's lovely. Fresh tarmac, a little sand on the very edges.
随着夕阳西下 以及车轮下的沥青路面
With the sun setting and tarmac beneath our wheels,
我们决定在天黑之前尽可能多赶赶路
we decided to knock off as many miles as possible before dark.
在白天的时候天气像蒸笼一样 但现在...
I'll admit that in the day, it is a bit toasty warm, but now...
刚刚过了七点
It's just gone seven o'clock.
刚刚日落西山
The sun has just gone down behind the hill there.
温度只有38度 太令人高兴了
This is absolutely delightful. A mere 38 degrees.
夜幕降临 我们把车停在路边安营扎寨
As night fell, we pulled off the road to make camp,
詹姆斯和我认为威尔曼先生 肯定在后备货车里放了一些豪华帐篷
with James and I assuming Mr Wilman had put some luxury tents in the backup van.
我正在努力回忆 我以前有没有像今晚这样烦躁过
I'm trying to remember if I've ever been as irritated as this.
太简陋了
It's pretty poor.
这...就这破条件 哪怕是童子军也会拒绝的
This is... Even a boy scout would say no to that.
这些帐篷他是从哪弄的
Where's he got them from?
他是不是在格拉斯顿伯里音乐节结束后随手拿的
Did he go to Glastonbury the day after it finished and just helped himself?
但我不能...我有...我已经63岁了
But I can't... I mean, I'm 63 years old.
我连我的膝盖都碰不到 更别说脚指了
I can barely touch my knees, leave alone my toes.
就这帐篷我早上起来怎么穿衣服
How does he think I'm going to get dressed in that in the morning?
你知道什么让我更烦躁吗
And do you know what's doubly irritating?
不知道 你说吧
No, but go on.
-哈蒙德的帐篷好多了 -好太多了
-Hammond's tent is better. -It's much better.
明知道六米开外的哈蒙德
I'm never going to be able to get to sleep
睡得比我舒服 这让我怎么睡得着
knowing that Hammond is having a better time 20 feet away.
我不想要这样的帐篷
I do not need a tent like that.
咱先不说其他 这帐篷是半透明的
It's translucent apart from anything else.
威尔曼先生是不是走进商店里说 "哪个帐篷最便宜"
Did he go into a shop and say, "What is the cheapest tent?"
"哪个帐篷最便宜"
"What is the cheapest tent?"
超市宣称会回收自己的购物袋...
You know supermarkets are claiming to recycle their carrier bags...?
经历了悲惨一夜后 我们继续向西南方向行驶
After a wretched night, we headed south-west
深入非洲的炎热地带
once more into the vast heat of Africa.
但从好的方面来看
But on the plus side,
这段旅程一开始 就仿佛置身于车迷的天堂
this leg of the journey started out as a slice of petrolhead heaven.
首先是砾石拉力赛
First, there was a gravel rally stage.
随后像是穿越了一条高山峡谷
And then, there was what felt like an alpine pass.
喔 沥青路面
Whoa, tarmac!
天啊 多么棒的一条路啊
Jesus! What a road!
再然后...
And then...
我们碰到了所有人都深恶痛绝的路面
We hit a surface that all of us absolutely hate.
天啊 就像是搓衣板
Oh God, it's washboard.
糟糕的路面
Oh, bad bit.
快结束吧 求求了 我求你了
Let it end. Now, please, I beg of you.
观众朋友们 你们可能不认为这路面很差 但请看
You might not believe this is bad, viewers, but look.
我有一个出风口已经被晃掉了
One of my air vents has been shaken free of the car.
从我们所处的位置来看 他掉落的出风口已经是最小的问题了
From where we were sitting, that was the least of his problems.
詹姆斯 你的玛莎拉蒂 看起来摇晃的很厉害
James, your Maserati looks very wobbly.
就像一辆快散架的 破旧的小丑车一样摇摇晃晃
Like fall apart clown car wobbly.
翼子板在晃 所有零件都在晃
The wings are moving, everything.
我的天啊 我看到你的意思了
Oh my God, I see what you mean.
整个车身都在颤抖
The whole body is vibrating.
确实是非常震颤
It's absolutely shocking in here.
你们觉得威尔曼先生会不会提前 在后援车里放一些备用骨盆呢
Do you think Mr Wilman thought to put some spare pelvises in the backup van?
天啊
Oh God.
这样的路面我们开了42公里
We have done 42 kilometres of this.
我受够了这他娘的搓衣板路
I'm sick of this. Fxxking washboard, fxxking road.
万幸的是 一座道路平坦的小镇 很快映入眼帘
Mercifully, a town with smooth roads soon hoved into view.
欣盖提 人口4711
温度 50摄氏度
这座欣盖提小镇 一千年前 真的是一千年前
This town, Chinguetti, a thousand years ago, and I do mean a thousand years ago,
曾经是通布图和海岸之间的中转站
was a staging post between Timbuktu and the coast,
所有的文献都存放在这里
and they stored all their literature here.
每栋建筑都曾经是一座图书馆 所有的知识都汇聚于这个小镇
Every building was a library. All of learning was in this town.
如今 这座小镇 被一条充满软沙的河谷一分为二
Today, the town is split in two by a Wadi full of soft sand.
而穿越这条河谷 需要巨大的速度和动力
And crossing it plainly required a vast amount of speed and power.
我的老天爷啊
Holy Jesus!
大猩猩来了
Jeremy's here.
这是个漂亮的小广场 不是吗
It's quite a nice little square, this, isn't it?
我的车现在看起来有点... 有点粗犷
My car's looking a little bit-It looks quite rugged now.
嘿 这是什么
And what's all this?
我不知道
Ah! I don't know.
天啊
Oh geeeee.
天啊 这可不妙
Geee, that's not good.
这本来是应该在某个容器里的
That's supposed to be inside somewhere.
-这是油还是水 还是油水 沙质油水 -都不是
Is it oil or water? Or oily water? -Sandy, oily water? -It's neither.
-这是转向助力油 -什么
-It's power steering fluid. -What?
由于在高温下的激烈驾驶
The power steering fluid is getting incredibly hot
转向助力油变得非常烫
because of all the work it's doing, and the heat.
你看到了吗...
Have you seen?
我看到引擎盖打开了 我应该...
I can see the bonnet's up, should I...
就是个小...就是温度的问题而已
Oh, it's just a minor... it's just the temperature,
就是这里稍微烫了一点...
-bit too much heat here and there.
它在哭啊
It's been crying.
是的 稍微哭了两下
Yeah, it has had a little weep.
DB9在沙漠里就会出现这种情况 这是众所周知的事情
Um, it's a known thing that they do it in the desert, DB9s.
嘿 听我说
Listen.
-我想在小镇上转一转 -好的
I wanna look round this town. -Yes.
我想看看这座小镇
I've got something I want to look at in this town.
-什么 不 我真心问 你想看什么
What? No, no, what?
图书馆
It's a library.
这里有很多图书馆 那里的 "Bibliotheque"就是图书馆的意思
There's lots of libraries. Look, "Bibliothèque", that means library.
一共有三间 曾经有七百间
There's three of them, I think. There used to be what, 700?
所有的知识  我说得对吗 基本上... -是的
All of knowledge, I'm right, aren't I, pretty much, was stored here.
-...全放在这 -所有的阿拉伯知识 没错
All of Arab knowledge, yes.
好的 我们一会儿见
Right, we'll see you in a minute.
我想四处看看这个历史遗址的原因
The reason why I wanted to look around this historical site
是因为很快 它就将不复存在
is because soon, it won't be here.
撒哈拉沙漠正在...吞噬这座小镇
The desert is... eating the town.
-什么 -正在吞噬
-What? -Is eating it.
天啊 快看这个
Bloody hell. Look at this.
他肯定不会再修剪草坪了 对吧
He's not gonna be mowing his lawn anymore, is he?
所以 深达好几十厘米 甚至是几米
So it's feet deep, metres deep.
-沙漠为什么要吞噬一座小镇 -快看那个
-Why is the desert eating the town? -Look at that!
是这样的 如今有件事叫作全球变暖
Well now, there's a thing called global warming.
听说过
Heard of that.
正因为全球变暖 撒哈拉沙漠正在以每年四米的速度
And because of it, the Sahara Desert is moving south
向南移动
at the rate of four metres a year.
所以 意思就是 风吹动沙子
So this is what, wind moving the sand?
就是...植被逐渐死亡 演变成为沙漠
Yes, it's just-Well, the vegetation is dying and becoming desert.
-一百年后 这里将变成一片沙漠 -一切都将不复存在
-Hundred years, all that's desert. -Gone.
那可能是房顶
That's probably the top of a house.
天啊...我太震惊了
Bloody-I'm staggered by this.
-这么跟你说吧 哈蒙德 -说什么
-Tell you what though, Hammond? -What?
我有了个想法
It has given me an idea.
什么想法
What?
你会很喜欢的
You're gonna like this.
与此同时 在其中一间图书馆里
Meanwhile, in one of the libraries,
我看到了一些难以置信的古代文字
I was being shown some incredible ancient texts.
这一小部分用的是真黄金
There's actual gold used in this bit,
这是黄金
this is gold.
是吗
Yeah.
这个是镀金的
It's gilded.
-是的 就是这个 -这个也太叹为观止了
Yeah, this one. It is stunning, this one.
他说有一位美国游客拜访过图书馆的负责人
Said that an American tourist visited the guy in the library,
美国人想让他把书卖给自己
and he asked him to sell him the book.
然后美国人告诉他 如果他愿意卖掉 就给他一套佛罗里达的房子
Then he told him if he would sell it, he's gonna give him a house in Florida, and he said no.
他拒绝了 说这是他曾祖父母的遗产
It's the legacy of his great-grandparents.
我觉得你做得对
I think you did the right thing.
你肯定不想要佛罗里达的房子
You don't want a house in Florida.
那里又热又粘 而且到处都是持枪人士
It's all hot and sticky and full of people with guns.
我能摸一下 这本500岁的天文学书吗
Can I touch a 500-year-old astronomy book?
这讲的是相对运动 是月球和...
This is the relative motions of the Moon and...
...地球和太阳的相对运动
the Earth and the Sun.
所以 这是在哥白尼之前的时代
So that's pre-Copernicus, presumably,
所以这本书大概也是同一时期的
so it's about the same time,
当时在阿拉伯世界 他们还没有认识到
and in the Arab world I don't think they had yet recognised
太阳应该被视为宇宙的中心
that the Sun should be considered in the middle.
而且别忘了...
Bear in mind as well that
我们说的11世纪 只是我们当下眼中的11世纪
what we're talking about here, the 11th century, is our understanding of the 11th century...
把图书管理员讲得昏昏欲睡之后
Having sent the librarians into a deep sleep,
船长终于出现在阳光下
James finally emerged into the sunlight.
嘿 怎么样好玩吗
Hey, how are you doing? Was it good?
好玩 真的是棒极了
Yeah, it was bloody fantastic.
有很多书 但有一本古老的书
Lots of books but this ancient one
上边有关于先知生活的图解
with diagrams in about lives of the prophets,
每一个都有插图
and every one was an illustration, like a picture.
-像画一样 -他马上就要变脸了
His mood is about to change.
你们干了什么好事
What have you done? What have you done?
-你们干了什么好事 -我们一直在到处闲逛
Well we've been hanging around. We've walked about,
我们四处走走 看了看这座小镇
looked at the town, haven't we?
-哦 你说这个啊 -你发现了 是啊
-You've noticed. -Oh that?
-不是我们干的 -没错
No.
-这是... -我们刚参观完镇上的另一侧
We got back from looking round this other bit of the town...
-回来后就看到了这个场景 -是的 没错
-Yes. -...and found this.
你听说过尘魔
You've heard of dust devils,
-有点像旋转的风 -是的
those little like spinning winds? -Yes.
你停车的位置 正处于这些街道的交叉口
Where you parked, at this intersection.
-好的 -我认为由此可能增大了风力
I think it maybe amplified the effect of the wind
导致风把沙子卷起来 全都堆在了你的车里
and just picked it up and deposited it there.
是你们亲眼所见吗
And you saw this happen?
不 我们没看到 因为我们刚才在逛小镇的另一边
No, we didn't, cos we were looking round the other town.
我们还能想到一件事
The only other thing we can think of,
-我们已经绞尽脑汁了... -是的
we've wracked our brains,
...他们这里不开罚单
is that they don't have tickets here,
- 如果你把车停在路中间 -没错
- if you park in the middle of the road. -Yeah.
交通协管员就会用沙子填满你的车
The traffic wardens simply fill your car with sand.
这理由真是...太妙了
That's a-that's very good.
但如果我的车坏了怎么办
But what if my car doesn't work?
-肯定没坏 -我怎样才能把沙子弄出来
And how the hell do I get it out?
-钥匙在哪里 -你刚才放哪里了
-Where's the key? -Ah. Where did you leave it?
我放在中控台上了
On the centre console, where I always leave it.
-把车门打开 沙子就出来了 -车门锁上了
If you just open the doors, the sand'll fall out. Well, it's locked.
我从来不锁车
You see, I never lock my car.
就是防止这种情况的发生
Just in case this exact thing happens.
好吧 给我一把铲子 我把沙子铲出来 你们...
OK, give me a shovel, I'll get it. You...
你们就滚蛋吧
Oh, bugger off then.
留下船长去解决 他那怪异的沙尘问题之后
Having left James to sort out his freak sandstorm issue,
我们找到了后援货车
we headed for the backup van,
因为我们决定解决
because we'd decided to solve the problems
可怕的搓衣板路带来的一系列问题
caused by the horrendous washboard roads.
天啊这是...
Oh God, it's a, it's a...
烫死了
Oh, burning, ah!
谢谢
Ah! Thank you.
如果想焊接...
If you wanna do any welding.
-或电锯 -或者角色扮演
Or chainsawing. Or role play.
稍等一下
Now hang on a minute.
我可以用这些做点什么
I could do something with these.
没错 我可以
Yes, I can.
当船长努力清空他的车时...
While James toiled away emptying his car...
真愚蠢
Oh, stupid.
我们忙于研究在货车里发现的东西
...we got busy with what we'd found in the van,
很快 我们用来应对搓衣板路的改装方案准备就绪
and soon our washboard solution modifications were ready.
我在货车里找到了这个
-So I found this in the truck. -Yes.
-这是一台耕耘机 -是的 没错
-It's a cultivator. -It is.
可能会起作用 但是通常情况下
It might work, but normally
耕耘机是拖在拖拉机后面的
cultivators are towed behind the tractor.
对 但那样的话 我得先开车走过崎岖路面
Yes, but I'd have to drive over the rough road
然后耕耘机把我身后的路铺平
before cultivating it level.
这样行不通
That wouldn't work.
但这样做可以造福别人啊
No, it would be more sociable.
我不想
I'm not.
-你不想造福别人 -没错
-You're not what, sociable? -Sociable.
我只想让自己舒服一点 让我的日子好过一点
I want this for me to work and make my life better.
但我觉得你会认为
But I think you'll find my solution
我的改装方案比你这个优秀几百万倍
surpasses this by a factor of several million.
我真不知道威尔曼先生 为什么明知我们要来撒哈拉沙漠
I've literally no idea why Mr Wilman put two snowmobiles in the van,
还要把两辆雪地摩托放进货车里 但我很高兴他这样做了
knowing we're going to the Sahara Desert, but I'm glad he did.
容我解释一下 好吗
Let me explain. OK.
我没用滑雪板 而是在前面装了轮子
Instead of using the skis, I've fitted wheels at the front,
但轮子并不是让我们感兴趣的部分
but we're not really interested in this.
我们感兴趣的是这些履带
What we are interested in is the tracks.
它们将在我的车轮前呼啸而过
They're gonna be whizzing along in front of my wheels,
抚平搓衣板路面上的
smoothing out the ridges
各种凸起
in the washboard.
所以 当我驶过后
So when I arrive,
路面会变得难以置信的光滑 就像一张台球桌
incredibly smooth, it'll be like a billiard table.
而且它们会像 两个巨大的带式砂光机一样运转
They're gonna be going eeeee, like two massive belt sanders?
是的 非常正确 它们就是带式砂光机
Yes. Exactly right, they're belt sanders,
安装在捷豹F-Type的前部
mounted to the front of a Jaguar F-Type.
-是的 -越野捷豹...越野F型
-Yeah. -Off road Jag. An F-Off roader type.
很不可思议吧与其被关在一个 单调乏味的精神病院单间
It's incredible, isn't it? Rather than be locked up in a drab cell,
穿着背后系扣的病号服
in a jacket that does up at the back,
不如有这么多机会 让你的疯狂点子变为现实
you've had so many opportunities to make your insanity real.
成果就在眼前
There it is!
随着技术简报会结束
With the technical briefings over,
是时候将理论付诸实践了
it was time to put theory into practice.
抬升设备
Raising rig.
理查德哈蒙德 驶向未来
Richard Hammond. To the future.
我猜这座小镇上的大多数人
I'm guessing that most of the people in this town
都还没见过雪地摩托
have not yet seen a snowmobile.
等他们听说了雪地摩托的用途后 肯定会感到非常惊讶
They're going to be quite surprised to hear what its primary purpose is.
显然 我现在把它放在高位
Obviously, I have it in a raised position right now.
我可以通过液压降低它的高度
I can hydraulically lower it.
就像007的那台路特斯
It's just like James Bond's Lotus.
在普通模式下 这就是一辆普通的汽车
In normal car mode, it's just a normal car.
来到城外的搓衣板路面之后
Once we came to a washboard section of road outside the town,
我们为首次测试做好了准备
we prepared for our maiden trial.
雪地摩托开始运转
Snowmobiles are running.
好了 我要开始了
Right, I'm doing it. I'm doing it.
开始 正在降低高度
Here we go. Lowering.
我们开始
And here we go.
天啊 我觉得它起作用了
By Jove, I think it's working.
我不...真的
I mean I... Yeah.
我正在雕刻道路 正在抚平道路
I am sculpting the roads. I'm smoothing them.
我正在平整道路
I am grading the road.
天啊
God!
真不敢相信眼前的一切
Cannot believe that this is happening.
太棒了
Oh yeah.
而我就坐在这里尽情放松
And I'll just sit here now and relax.
要记住 受益人不只我一个
And it's not just me that's benefitting. Remember that.
整个非洲都会由此受益
The whole of Africa is benefitting.
石头被弹起来了 快看 耕耘机弹起了很多石头
Oh, stones are coming. See, it's kicking up some stones.
没错 会有这种情况发生
Oh yeah, that can happen. Yeah.
天啊 有几块大石头
Oh yeah, that's some big stones.
但尽管存在这个小问题
But despite this teething problem,
当我们在几公里后靠边停车 检查作业情况时
when we pulled over a few miles later to inspect our work,
结果是毫无疑问的
the results were unquestionable.
看看左手边的道路
You look on the left-hand side of the road, which is what we have graded,
也就是我们平整过的那一侧
that side,
然后再看看右手边 也就是我们没有平整过的一侧
and then look at the right-hand side of the road, which we haven't graded,
-这就是...证据 -起作用了
-I mean it... proof. -It works, it works.
-这条路上简直都能跑F1了 -太简单了
-You could run an F1 race on that. -Oh, easy.
随后我们决定满怀公益精神
We then decided to be fully public spirited,
齐头并进 这样就能把所有路面全都抚平
and drive side by side, so we could smooth out all of the road.
好了 哈蒙德 我们出发吧
OK, Hammond, let's go.
我们可以同时平整两条车道
We could do dual carriageways.
我感觉我可以更深一些
I reckon I can go a bit deeper here.
就是要...我正在学习 如何巧妙地运用这个系统
Just gotta... I'm learning to finesse the system now.
糟糕
Shit!
不好了
Oh shit!
我的天啊
Oh, my God!
我从来没有见过这样的事情
I've never seen anything like it.
我看到了一股烟 然后雪地摩托就开走了 然后...
I just saw a puff of smoke and it leapt that thing and...
但至少没有目击者 除了这辆卡车上的人之外
At least there are no witnesses. Apart from the people in this lorry.
-我现在要静静地开过去 -是啊
-I'm just gonna quietly move along. -Yeah.
好了
Right.
只要我跟你一起走 人们就不会发现少了一台雪地摩托
If I drive alongside, people won't spot that there's one missing.
是的 好主意 哈蒙德
Yeah, good thinking Hammond.
刚才那场景也太独特了 我也很有信心
Well, that was unique. I'm pretty confident...
我觉得耕耘机坏了
Oh, I think it just broke.
在第二次事故后 我们决定
After this second incident, we decided to abandon all road mending
放弃眼下所有的道路修补工作
for the foreseeable future.
起初 我们的实验结果非常出色
Initially, our experiment was brilliant, and then everything went
后来局面变得非常糟糕 急转直下
terribly, badly wrong...
真的是急转直下
very quickly indeed.
你准备演讲稿了吗 我准备了
Had you prepared speeches? I had.
我之前不知道自己会得 司令勋章还是官佐勋章
I didn't know whether I'd get a CBE or an OBE.
我本来指望人们为我立一尊雕像 然后请我去TED演讲
I was gonna get a statue and do a TED talk.
恐怕现在两个我都得不到了
I'm probably not gonna get either now,
特别是考虑到我的雪地摩托 可能撞进了了一座偏远的村庄
particularly if my snowmobile crashes into a remote village.
我们觉得船长最后肯定会赶上来
Assuming May would eventually catch up,
所以决定先行一步
we decided to press on.
但是 随着夜幕降临 我的马丁再次开始作妖
But, as darkness fell, my Aston began to play up. Again.
我又过热了
Er, I'm just overheating again.
我的车让我立即停车
I've been told to stop immediately by the car.
我好像没法挂到三档以上 所以转速太高了
I can't seem to get past third gear, so it's running at too high RPM.
好吧 哈蒙德
OK, Hammond. Um,
我真的一点儿忙也帮不上
there's literally nothing I can do about that.
不会吧 太遗憾了 但你说得对
No, that was a sigh, but you're right.
随着同事的尾灯消失在夜色中
As my colleague's taillights dissolved into the night,
我独自一人继续前行
I was left to trundle on... alone.
已经很晚了 而且我的车速 不能超过每小时32公里
Er, it's late and I can't go much more than 20 miles an hour.
变速箱失灵了 没法升档
The gearbox is failing. It won't shift up.
我卡在第二档了
I'm stuck in second.
而且只要我的转速超过 每分钟1500
And if I run it any higher than one and a half thousand RPM,
发动机就会过热
the engine overheats.
此外 我收到了车辆的警告
Also I'm getting warnings telling me check battery off switch,
让我检查电池 关闭开关 刹车故障 安全停车
brake failure, stop safely and my dashboard lights have gone out.
仪表盘的灯也灭了 又亮了
Oh, they've come back!
"急需保养SRS安全气囊
SRS airbag service urgent.
"翻车保护出现故障 需要进行DSC保养"
Rollover protect fault. DSC service required.
加油啊
Come on.
得带你去营地 稍微修理一下
Gonna get you to camp. Bit of work.
第二天早上 船长和我汇合了
The next morning, James and I were reunited.
天啊
Oh God.
我尿完了
Oh I'm empty.
-早上好 梅 -早上好
-Morning, May. -Morning.
你知道画面里少了什么吗
Have you seen what's missing from this picture?
知道
Yes.
我在他俩后面 他们领先我几公里
I am behind the other two. They're some miles ahead.
我会赶上他们的
I will find them,
但我现在要把车修好 否则寸步难行
but I can't go on any further, until I've sorted this car.
所以 我昨晚在这里小憩了一晚 因为我可以
So I kipped here last night, cos I can,
毕竟我有一家阿斯顿马丁酒店
cos I've got an Aston Martin hotel.
但这台阿斯顿马丁运转得不是很顺畅
But the Aston Martin bit isn't working very well.
现在的情况是 我出席了这款车的发布会
I did the launch of this car.
我记得刚发布的时候
I remember when they came out.
恰恰是汽车开始变得更加智能的时刻
It's from the exact point when cars started getting cleverer.
但智能程度还不够
But not clever enough.
通常而言 汽车上所有的电子部件
Normally everything on the car electric
都是通过独立的线路控制的
was controlled by a separate wire,
这种情况下 如果你只有一个喇叭 那还可以接受
which is OK when all you had was a horn.
但如今 所有部件 都是通过电子设备来操作的
But by this time, everything was worked with electronics,
所以他们把所有线路 合并成了一条巨大又智能的线路
so they combined them all into one gigantic, very clever wire
绕着全车走 连接不同的零件
that went all the way round the car and stopped off at all the different things.
汽车可以感知到一切 比如刹车 悬挂系统
And the car can feel everything, its brakes, its suspension,
这非常棒 但一旦感知不到的时候 就出问题了
which is great, until it can't feel them.
所以 如果车辆感觉不到变速箱了 就会停用变速箱
So if it can't feel its gearbox, it stops using its gearbox.
这里面的某个地方有东西短路了
Somewhere in there is one little thing that's just shorting across,
导致整个中央神经系统陷入瘫痪
and it's sending the whole of its central nervous system into meltdown.
出问题的可能是这里任何一处
And it could be anywhere in there.
而沙漠环境更是雪上加霜
What's made it worse, is the desert.
太烫了 到处都是石头和沙子
It's hot. Full of stones and sand.
太烫了 需要冷却一下
It's hot, so it needs cooling.
这前面是一个小小的散热器 一个很小的冷却器
Here is a little radiator at the front, tiny little cooler.
这是用来冷却变速箱的油 变速箱位于后部
That cools oil for the gearbox, which is right at the back.
有一颗石头穿透了散热器 打了一个洞
One of the stones has gone through the radiator, and made a hole.
导致油漏了出来 溅到了散热器前侧
That's allowed the oil to leak out and spread over the front of the radiator,
再与沙子混合 相当于在它面前砌了一堵砖墙
mingle with the sand and build a brick wall in front of itself.
因此 变速箱过热
So the gearbox is overheating.
这个问题 我或许能做些什么 但对于电子部件
That I could probably do something about, but as for the electronics,
我只能不断地寻找
I'm just gonna have to look
直到我找到一个可以修复的故障
until I can physically find a problem to mend.
经过一个小时的调整后 我重新上路了
After an hour of fettling, I got back on the road,
但这台马丁却完全没有修好
but the Aston was by no means mended.
车还在开 这是件好事 但我只有一档
I'm moving, which is good. But I've only got one gear
而且我不知道 是发动机还是哪里出了什么故障
and I've no idea what's happening to the engine or anything else
因为我的仪表都不起作用 温度什么的 全都不显示了
cos none of my gauges are working. Temperature, nothing.
所以车子不让我换档
That's why it's not letting me change gear.
车子没有给我任何信息 因为它自己没有收到任何信息
It's not giving me any information because it's not getting any information.
你好啊 加油车
Oh, hello. The fuel bowser.
我不知道我的车是不是还有油 但我还是加一点吧
Well, I've no idea if I've got any fuel, but I'll get some anyway.
我的仪表不显示
My gauge doesn't work.
-看 -他来了
-Oh, look. -Here he is.
-你的车能动了 -是的 起码能动了
-It's working! -Yes. More or less.
我要让它休息一下
I'm just gonna give it a rest.
-你有几个档位 -一个
-How many gears have you got? -One.
-几档 -我不知道
I don't know.
真是糟糕透了 对了 加油
Absolute catastrophe. Right, fuel.
-我都不知道我需不需要加油 -是的 我没有...
-I've no idea if I need it. -I didn't have...
-没有仪表 -仪表不显示了
-You've no dials. -I've got nothing!
而且会发出这种声音 我不知道是怎么回事
It does that as well. I don't know what that is.
从来没听过007的马丁会发出这种声音
You never heard Bond's Aston sounding like that, did you?
听起来很棒
-Sounds brilliant.
邦德 你刚才开得多快
How fast were you going, Bond?
"不知道 车速表坏了 我只有一个档位
"I don't know. Speedo were broken. I only had one gear."
-你们知道吗 -什么
-Do you know what? -What?
-我们来这里三天了... -是的
-We've been here three days. -Yeah.
-我应该喝了有60升水 -肯定的
-I must have drunk 60 litres of water. -Easy.
我一次都没尿过 而现在
I haven't peed once and now I think this has encouraged it.
我听着加油声来感觉了 我感觉要嘘嘘
I can feel one coming. I'm gonna go for a slash.
-我得去尿一下 -我还没尿过
-I haven't had a pee. -No, don't need it!
不 不需要 太阳已经把我们晒熟了 但是...
Well, the sun has boiled it all out of us. But...
-其实是... 不 说实话 从来到这里...我还没尿过
But it's actually got-No, genuinely, I haven't had a pee since I got here.
-我要去尿一下 -我要试一试 已经有一阵子了
Go and have one. I'm gonna try, because it's been a while.
我还是没有尿意
I definitely still don't want one.
摆好姿势几分钟之后
After a few minutes of assuming the position,
我们或多或少都取得了些成功
we finally had some sort of success.
你知道那种小便颜色的对照图表
You know you get those charts that tell you the colour of your pee.
-根据尿的颜色告诉你健康状况 -怎么了
-It tells you how healthy you are. -Yeah.
图表上根本没有我这种颜色
This colour's not on that chart.
这简直就是 一股热沙从牛奶吸管里流出
This is just a thin stream of hot sand falling through a milk straw.
我的更像是楼梯扶手
Mine's like a stair banister.
我甚至都可以拔丝 让它变成一块太妃糖
I could actually pull it, and it's made a toffee.
下周说不定还能再搞一次
Might do that again in another week.
我的车座太烫了
Ah! My seat is so hot.
点火开启 仪表盘关闭
Ignition on. Dashboard off.
可以了 有前进档么
That is working. Do I have drive?
是的 能用了
No, yes, I do.
-怎么回事 -刚才是怎么回事...什么
What the...? What?
刚才是怎么回事
What the hell was that?
什么 怎么会...
What? Why would it...?
你为什么要把它绑在加油车上
Why did you tie it to the fuel bowser?
刚才咱俩在...
You and I were...
梅
May.
-是你干的吗 -什么
What?
有人把这个绑在加油车上了
Well, somebody tied it to the fuel bowser.
如果加油车爆炸了怎么办
What if the fuel bowser had blown up?
我知道是怎么回事了
Oh, I know what that is.
这些怪异的气象条件 可以把四处飘荡的一小段带子
The freaky meteorological conditions can tangle up
缠绕起来 然后把它绑在物体上
a stray bit of strop blowing around, and tie it onto things.
这可是我的家啊
That's my home.
我没办法再把它装回去了
I can't put it back on.
-摔碎了 -真不走运 我们走吧
-Cos it's smashed. -What a rotten bit of luck. Let's go.
这意味着 我们将看到一辆穿越沙漠的阿斯顿马丁DB9
That means we're going to have to look at an Aston Martin DB9 driving through the desert
而不是伦敦出租...
and not...a Metrocab
这就是工作场合的霸凌
This is bullying in the workplace.
不是我 我刚才在撒尿... 好吧 不是尿
I didn't do it! I was having a piss. Well, it wasn't a piss.
我其实是从体内射出了一点巧克力糖
I was ejecting some Rolos from my body.
哈蒙德 你的车太漂亮了
That's a beautiful car you've got there, Hammond.
闭嘴
Shut up.
我们今天的计划是抵达首都努瓦克肖特
Today our plan was to reach the capital city of Nouakchott.
鉴于我们都认为时间很充裕
And as we didn't think that would take too long,
所以我建议临时参观一些当地的文化
I suggested a cultural diversion.
我昨天在那个图书馆外面
I was talking yesterday to um,
跟一位老妇人聊天
an old woman outside that library,
她说如果我们沿着这条路一直走
and she said if we keep going down this road,
就能到达沙漠中那只巨大的眼睛
we get to this enormous eye in the desert.
什么
What?
听说它被称为非洲之眼
Apparently, it's called the Eye of Africa.
应该是地球上最奇妙的景观了
It's supposed to be the most amazing thing on Earth.
是吗
Is it?
那就是个奇特的地理现象
It's a weird geological event.
但也有人说那就是失落的亚特兰蒂斯城
But some people say it's the Lost City of Atlantis.
其实之前根本没人发现
It was actually-Nobody knew about it
直到被阿波罗计划的宇航员从太空中看到
until the Apollo astronauts saw it from space.
真的吗
Really?
我知道这听起来难以置信 但她就是这么说的
I know it sounds implausible, but that's what she said.
她是不是还想卖给你一些魔豆来着
Did she also try and sell you some magic beans?
如果我们能开快一点
If we pick up the pace a bit,
就有时间去找它了
we'd have the time to spend a little while looking for it.
我开不快 我只有一个档位
I can't pick up the pace. I've got one gear.
那这样 我和梅可以组成先遣队
Well, listen, May and I can form an advance party by picking up the pace, all right?
找到之后通知你
And when we find it, we'll give you a bell.
如果你们能顺便找到备用帐篷 我将不胜感激
If you find a spare tent as well, I'd be grateful.
非洲之眼 我来了
Taking me to the Eye of Africa. Here I come!
大口喝油吧 我的增压发动机
That super charger. Eat. Eat fuel!
除了那只巨大的眼睛 沙漠里还有什么
What else is out there in the desert, along with the gigantic eye?
一个巨大的鼻子
A massive nose.
我知道那里还有一对大奶子
I know there's a pair of huge tits out there.
在顺滑的沥青路面上飞驰了一段之后
Having made good progress on the smooth tarmac,
詹姆斯和我来到了那只神秘的眼睛附近
James and I were nearing the location of the mysterious eye.
听着 詹姆斯 如果那位老妇人的话可信的话
OK, James. If the old woman is to be believed
那只巨大的眼睛应该就在这里了
the gigantic eye is along here.
我没看到有眼睛
There isn't an eye.
等你爬上那座山就看见了
Well, you won't be saying that when you crest that hill,
你就瞧好吧
and there's an enormous eye there. You just watch.
好几公里之外的后方
A good few miles back,
我跟他俩汇合的几率愈发渺茫
my chances of joining the other two were becoming slimmer.
仪表刚刚短暂显示了一下 但全都是坏消息
Right, gauges have just come on briefly, and it's bad news,
水温很高
temperature really high.
我唯一能做的就是 根据声音判断
All I can do is proceed at what pitch tells me
保持2000的转速 用唯一的档位行驶
is 2,000 RPM in my one gear,
我还可以停车 把车顶升起来
and I could do with stopping and putting my roof up.
我要在这个壮观的村庄广场停下来
I'm gonna pull up in this magnificent village square,
因为我快被晒熟了
because I'm being cooked.
我投降
I give in.
他俩敢放下顶棚 我不行
They can drive with their roofs off. I'm not brave enough.
千万别卡住
Please don't be stuck.
噢不 不要这样
Oh God! No, that's not acceptable.
天啊 怎么了
Christ, I've just ...
这是在撞车时才会弹出的防滚架
That's the rollover that deploys in a crash.
好吧
That's good.
事已至此 没什么好顾虑的了
Well, it can't happen again, can it? It's gone.
我看看
It's just see... ah.
我刚试着启动 但...
Um, I just tried to start it, and it's, it's...
局面真是急转直下
Things just got a lot worse really quickly!
与此同时 在沙漠深处
Meanwhile, deep in the desert,
我们还没找到苦苦寻觅的非洲之眼
we still hadn't found what we were looking for.
找不到 找不到
No eye, no eye, no eye.
只有骆驼 骆驼有眼睛 但不是非洲之眼
Camels, camels' eyes, but no eyes.
天啊 这噪音太可怕了
Christ, that is a terrible noise!
克拉克森 这样做有什么意义 根本没有什么大眼睛
What is the point of this, Clarkson? There is no giant eyeball.
我们就是在毁车
We're just wrecking the cars.
再坚持一下 翻过那座山
For a bit more persevering we might just get over that crest there,
你就能看到了
and there it is.
完蛋
Bollocks!
见鬼
Cock!
我陷车了 都怪你
I'm stuck, and it's your fault.
所有那些从太空中能看到的景观
All this stuff about seeing from outer space.
比如中国的长城
Think about the thing, the Great Wall of China,
"你可以从太空看到长城"
famously "you can see that from out of space."
在它旁边也应该能看到啊
You can also see it when you're standing next to it.
肯定在这儿 你就是不让我去找
It is there. You just, you won't let me go and have a look for it.
也可能那只是某个老巫婆给你讲的童话故事
Or it might have been a fairytale that Gypsy Rose told you,
因为你给了她一点零钱
because you'd given her £1.50.
好吧好吧 咱们不找了
All right, all right, fine, well I'll-we'll give in.
虽然我不喜欢半途而废 但我放弃了
I don't like giving in, but I'm going to give in.
本来在非洲到处找一只眼睛这件事就很可笑
Yeah, but you're giving in looking for something like an eye in the middle of Africa.
-可她说过是一只巨大的眼睛 -有多大
-Yes, it's a huge eye. -Huge, but how huge?
就是...按照她的描述应该非常巨大
Well, it's, the way she described it, like massive huge.
-对了 哈蒙德在哪里 -这是个好问题
-Where's Hammond, by the way? -That is a good question.
我觉得他根本没心思来找非洲之眼
I'm assuming he's not bothered to coming to look at the eye
因为他认为这是...
cos he just thinks...
好吧 我知道这个举动可能毫无意义 但是...
OK, I know this is probably a pointless exercise, but let's...
根本没有信号
No signal at all.
手机一点用也没有
That is of no help.
没有大量液体流出
There's no huge amounts of fluid that've come out,
但即使有也无法解释
but even if they had, that wouldn't explain it just being
为什么无法启动
dead at the key.
显然是电气系统的问题
It's clearly electrics.
如果这颗2005年的脆弱大脑坏死
If its feeble 2005 brain has given up,
那我就完蛋了
I've had it.
唯一的另一种可能是电池
The only other thing, battery.
应该还有电对吧
That's not gone flat has it?
电池在...
But it's behind
座椅后边
this seat.
谢天谢地
Oh dear Lord! Salvation!
等等 让我试一下
No way. Hang on, let me just check.
原来是电极松了
The live battery terminal has shaken loose.
应该是这一路的颠簸所致
Literally this has shaken itself undone. It was like that.
我上路了 好消息接连不断
I got going, and there was more good news,
我的变速箱决定恪守本职
because the gearbox had decided to actually be a gearbox again.
阿斯顿马丁好样的
Aston Martin! Yeah ha ha ha!
档位什么的全都恢复了
I've got gears, and everything.
与此同时 在我们回到主干路的途中
Meanwhile, on our way back to the main road,
我和梅被眼前的东西分散了注意力
May and I had been rather distracted by something we had found.
请看
This.
天啊 快看这个
Bloody Nora, look at this!
嘿 快看
Hey, look!
我的老天爷啊
Jesus wept!
这是绿洲吗
Is that an oasis?
没有证据能表明我是英国人
Literally no evidence that I'm English.
等一下
Wait.
过来坐吧 我这里有应景的音乐
Come and have a seat. I've got just the thing we should be listening to.
我找不到任何东西来纪念...
I can't find anything to commemorate the
理查德哈蒙德的去世
demise of Richard Hammond.
你知道吗 戈登莱特福特也是今天去世的
You know Gordon Lightfoot also died today. So...
-是吗 -是的
-Did he? -Yeah.
Gordon Lightfoot – If You Could Read My Mind
♪ If you could read my mind, love ♪
♪ What a tale my thoughts could tell ♪
♪ Just like an old time movie ♪
♪ 'Bout a ghost from a wishing well ♪
♪ In a castle dark or a fortress strong ♪
♪ With chains upon my feet ♪
♪ You know that ghost is me ♪
♪ And I will never be set free ♪
♪ As long as I'm a ghost, you can't see ♪
我来告诉你们毛里塔尼亚有多空旷
Just to give you an idea of how empty Mauritania is,
我在这条贯穿整个国家的主干路上
I've now done a hundred miles on this, the main road
跑了160公里
from one side of the country to the other,
一辆车都没见到
and I haven't seen another car, not one, nothing.
就是...让人头疼
It's just... it hurts your head,
这个地方的广阔和空旷
the bigness of this place, and the emptiness.
我觉得前面有一辆被毁了容的阿斯顿马丁...
I do believe it's a disfigured Aston Martin.
是的 没错
Yes, it is.
同事们追上了我
My colleagues caught up with me
而我这辆闹鬼的车又开始作妖了
just as my haunted car started to play up... again.
变速箱再次失灵
I've lost gearbox.
现在开始哔哔作响了
Oh, now it's beeping!
车窗怎么打开了
Why have my windows opened?
怎么回事...我没动啊
Why have my... who... I didn't ask them.
我的车窗怎么打开了
Why have my windows opened?
它现在不光不服从我 而且还折磨我
It's actively disobeying and tormenting me now.
我的车自行决定打开车窗并剥夺我换档的能力
It's, uh, decided to open the windows, and take away the ability to change gear,
伴随着令人抓狂的哔哔声
accompanied by a maddening beep.
我认为我的车之所以发出哔哔声
I thought the beeping might be happening
是因为它觉得我的车顶没有固定牢靠
because the car didn't believe my roof was secured properly.
所以我把车停在路边 验证我的猜想是否正确
So, I pulled over to test my theory.
混蛋
Bastard!
还在响
It's still beeping!
这车的设计真是便捷 按一个按钮把车顶收起来
It's got a very convenient roof, you just press the button, and it goes down,
然后还得下车边跳边往下按
and then you have to get out and jump on it.
我确实听说人在沙漠里待久了就会被逼疯
They do say that people are driven mad in the desert after a while.
试试中间这块
What about in the middle? The bit in the middle.
真是个野小子
Such a yobbo.
别哔哔了 没关系的
Just stop beeping! It's all right!
你刚才是说 你觉得你可能在二档吗
Did you say you thought you might be in second gear?
我的车不愿意告诉我 可我觉得是二档
Well, it won't tell me what gear I'm in, but I think it's second, yes.
但如果我车速再快一点 车就会迅速过热
But if I go any faster, it overheats very quickly.
詹姆斯 我们再次面临两难的境地 不是吗
James, once again we face a dilemma, don't we?
要么以60公里的时速开到海边
We drive all the way to the coast at 38 miles an hour,
要么...不这样做
or... we don't.
容我稍稍思考一下
Let me think about that one for a bit.
我想也是
I've come to the same conclusion.
妥妥的俩混蛋
Absolute bastards.
距离首都还有320公里
There were still 200 miles to go to the capital.
詹姆斯和我在一座小镇歇脚
So James and I pulled over in a small town
与加油车汇合
to rendezvous with the fuel bowser.
然后有了意想不到的发现
And we got an unexpected bonus.
-这是一条跑道 -是的
This is a runway. Yes.
我在想 也许...
I'm just thinking maybe...
趁着等哈蒙德的时候
while we're waiting for Hammond,
我们可以做点汽车节目该做的事
we could do some car stuff in our car programme.
你有什么想法
What do you have in mind?
我觉得可以来一场直线竞速赛
Well, I'm thinking of a drag race.
这主意可太妙了
Oh, what a good idea.
其实这还是挺有意思的
It'd be quite interesting, if you think about it.
我从一开始就在想这件事
And I have wanted to know actually since we set off.
你的车动力比我的强劲很多 你有...
You've got a lot more power than I have, haven't you? You've got...
我的动力更强劲 我有434匹马力 但我的车更沉
I've got more power. I've got 434, but I've got more weight.
你有434匹马力
You're 434 horsepower.
我有375匹 这辆车多重
I'm 375. How much does this weigh?
两吨
2 tons.
我的是1.6吨
Cos I'm 1.6.
-是啊 -有意思
-It'd be quite... -Interesting...
对屏幕前的各位来说 这是个有趣的实验
It'd be an interesting experiment, for the ladies and gentlemen.
没错
Yes.
欣然决定之后 我们向跑道尽头驶去
And so, with that decided, we headed to the end of the runway,
搭建了一些直线竞速赛的用具
erected some drag race paraphernalia,
然后准备出发
and prepared for the off.
好了 我需要做什么 运动模式 没错
Right, what do I need? Sport mode, yes!
牵引力控制系统也关了吧
Traction control, I think off.
我现在是手动模式 但由于我对这辆车的特殊改装
I'm in manual, but due to the unique way I've modified this car,
我无法更改任何程序设定
I'm unable to change any of the programs.
由于你对我这辆车的特殊填沙行为
Well, due to the unique way you filled my car with sand,
有几个按钮坏了 但现在搞定了
I have some trouble with the buttons, but I've got it now.
等一下 看看是谁来了
Wait a minute. Look who's here.
终结者3：机器的崛起
Terminator 3: Rise of the Machines.
-来得正是时候 -什么
-Just in time. -What?
-你来得正是时候 -干什么
-Just in time. -What for?
直线竞速赛
Drag race.
我现在不适合参加直线竞速赛
I'm not really in a position to do a drag race.
-熄火 -别别别
-Turn it off. -Ah, no, no, no.
可使不得
That would be a poor move.
为什么
Why can't you turn it off?
有可能再也打不着了
It probably will never start again.
我们刚才差点就开始比赛了
You know we were on the verge of starting a very tense drag race?
你们看过《终结者3》吗
Have you seen Terminator 3?
多年来人们一直好奇
People have wondered for many years
天网是什么时候觉醒自我意识的
when would Skynet become fully self-aware.
没想到居然是你在毛里塔尼亚驾驶的阿斯顿马丁里
In an Aston Martin being driven by you in Mauritania,
谁都没料到
no one saw that coming.
如果这个白痴开始跟其他机器交流该怎么办
What if this idiot learns to communicate with other machines.
-太蠢了 不是吗 -真是太蠢了
-It is moronic, isn't it? -It's a moron!
-呃 哈蒙德 -怎么了
-Uh, Hammond, Hammond. -What?
那是什么
What's that?
那台雪地摩托怎么在这儿
What the bloody hell is that doing here?
那不是你的吗
Is that one of yours?
-什么叫我的 -还能是谁的
-What do you mean, one of mine? -Well...What else is it going to be?
它自动驾驶多久了
How long has it been going?
从它被放生开始
Since he let it loose.
那可是240公里之外 噢不
That was 150 miles away. Oh Jesus!
你把它放生到沙漠里了
You released it into the desert.
不会吧
What that, it's...
天啊
Jeez!
-全都怪你 -什么
-That was your fault. -What?
那是你的雪地摩托 撒哈拉没有这玩意
Well, it was your snowmobile. They aren't any others in the Sahara.
我怎么能料到
I can't possibly have predicted that it would hit the fuel bowser.
它会从240公里开外精准击中加油车
From 150 miles away.
-你把它放生了 -是它自己挣脱的
-You released it into the wild. -I didn't release it. It escaped!
-威尔曼先生让我们规矩一点 -是的
-We were told to behave ourselves. -Yes.
我觉得我们该走了
I think we should depart.
是的 我们该走了
Yeah, we should go. Um...
-现在吗 -没错
-Fairly quickly? -Yes.
拜托请换档
Please change gear.
现在可以换档了
Change gear now.
现在是时候了 现在...就是现在
Now! Now is the time. It's-now is the time.
别跟我争 现在是换档的时候了
Don't argue with me. Now is the time to change gear!
詹姆斯和我大步流星地赶着路
James and I covered ground at a brisk pace,
尽量远离刚才的爆炸现场
putting as much distance between us and the explosion as possible.
很快我们就沉浸在了
And soon we became consumed
周围环境的凄凉之美中
by the stark beauty of our surroundings.
这里的景色 尤其是那一侧
The view on both sides, especially that side,
太壮观了
is spectacular.
简直就像雪丘一样
It's almost like snow dunes,
沙子是如此洁白
the sand is so pale.
非常梦幻
It's fantastic.
我的车显示温度已经降到37度了
My temperature has plummeted to 37.
是的 我的降到38度了
Oh yes, I'm down to 38.
"冷"得恰到好处
Wow! That's positively chilly.
终于 杰里米和我到达了首都
Eventually, Jeremy and I arrived in the capital city,
事实很快证明 我们在这里
where it soon became clear that we aren't as well known
并不像在世界其他地方那样出名
as we are in other parts of the world.
理查德
Richard!
有人刚刚喊我理查德
Somebody just called me "Richard."
如果那名年轻人想看真理查德的话
If the young man wanted to see the real Richard,
他还要等上很久
he'd be waiting a long while,
毕竟哈蒙德跟终结者处得很不愉快
given how Hammond and the Terminator were getting on.
醒一醒 你个混蛋
Come back. Work, you twat.
我们就不能...我知道变速箱在你身上
Can we not just-OK, it's your gearbox.
但能不能把它视作是我们的变速箱
Can we think of it as our gearbox?
我们共用一个变速箱
We both, we share a gearbox.
中控锁刚刚启动了
The central locking just went off.
把车门锁上了
It just locked its doors.
几小时后
Several hours later,
天网推着我只有一个档位的车 驶入努瓦克肖特
Skynet propelled my one gear car into Nouakchott,
我终于能找到稳定的无线网络
where there was good enough Wi-Fi
让我连接诊断笔记本
for me to connect the car's malfunctioning brain
一窥这颗失控的大脑
to a diagnostic laptop.
好吧 一个档位跑了320公里
Right, 200 miles on one gear.
通过笔记本 我在用0和1跟它交流
So laptop, I'm talking to it in zeros and ones,
用它能够理解的计算机语言
the language it understands.
我倒要看看他到底在怕些什么
And I'm now going to see what it's panicking about.
他操心的事情可真多 我的天啊
It's worrying about a lot. Oh my God!
车门模块
I'm in passenger door model,
这辆车在担心车门 担心变速箱
it's worrying about its door. Worry about your gearbox.
全球定位模块 这就是它说我在诺丁汉的原因
Global positioning module, that's why I was in Nottingham.
我相信这里面大部分都不是机械故障
I don't believe most of these are mechanical faults.
车本身没出什么问题 就是不太爽
Nothing's gone wrong. It's just got upset.
如果我按下这个按钮
If I hit this,
本质上就是"别担心"
this is basically the "don't worry" button.
我要按了
I'm going to do it.
忘了这些吧 系统正在清理故障码
Forget about it. It's clearing them.
请把车辆的控制权还给我
Please, give me control of the car,
让我驾驶
and let me drive.
但愿...我不敢看
So, hopefully... Can't look.
好了 这下好了
Yeah! There you go!
它没有要抱怨的了
That's nothing to moan about.
我应该可以换挡了
So I think I've got gears.
努瓦克肖特 人口150万
第二天早上 当我们出发四处闲逛时
The next morning, as we set off to look around town,
见证奇迹的时刻到了
it was the moment of truth.
我的车换档了 真的换挡了
It changed gear! It changed gear! It changed gear!
我有档位了 刚刚换档成功了
I've got gears. It just changed gear.
约翰康纳: 电影《终结者》中的角色，人类反抗军领袖
约翰康纳开始反击了
So, John Connor, you're fighting back.
没错
Oh yes!
我们本来只是随便逛逛 但没过多久
Our aim was to do a bit of sightseeing, but immediately we got distracted
我们就被这里汽车的英姿所深深吸引
by the heroic brilliance of Mauritania's cars.
看哪 这辆车完全趴地了
Yes, the suspension's gone.
他刚刚撞上了 撞车了
He's just crashed. He just crashed.
我也听到了
Is that what that noise was?
这辆车之所以会被撞成这样
Maybe, one explanation for some of the crashes that happened to this car
原因之一是你根本看不清车外
is the fact that you can't see out of it.
他们打算把车开到什么时候啊
When, when does it stop being a car?
完全动不了的时候吧 在那之前都能凑活开
I suppose when it stops moving. Until then, it's a car.
正开着呢就突然报废了
I think one day it's driving on, and just disappears.
-呃 -太危险了
-Eww. -Oh, that wasn't good.
快躲开 他没打算停车
He's going to keep, he's gonna keep going.
-你真棒 -他停不了车
-Fantastic. -He can't stop.
-小伙子有一只手要抓着车门 -看这辆
-That bloke got to hang on to the door. -Another one.
我喜欢前面竖着的行人保护装置
I like the pedestrian safety feature.
但这辆车还能开啊
But it's working! It's...
哈蒙德 再瞧瞧你
Hammond you worried about your Aston, and honestly...
和眼前所见相比
Well, that's why I can't make a fuss, isn't it? I mean,
我确实不应该小题大做
I've only kind of started.
看了一圈毛里塔尼亚战马之后
Having lapped up these Mauritanian war horses,
我们决定找个咖啡厅喝一杯...
we decided to go to a café for a drink...
热腾腾的黄褐色液体
of hot brown water.
我想知道这里的检测场长什么样
What does an MOT testing centre look like here I wonder.
-隐形的 -快看那辆奔驰
-Invisible. -Ah! A Mercedes. Look,
-每块面板都不止修过一次 -不止一次
-every panel, more than once. -Not just once.
都是岁月的痕迹啊
Oh yeah, that's a lifetime's work.
说说你的车吧 约翰 天网仍然占据上风吗
And, John, how's your car, or is Skynet still winning?
我对抗它 它反击我
I'm fighting it, and it's fighting back.
莎拉康纳: 电影《终结者》中的角色，约翰康纳的母亲
它有没有问 "你是莎拉康纳吗"
Has it said, "Are you Sarah Connor?"
博格人:《星际迷航》中的虚构种族，半机械生化人
我在考虑加入博格人来正面对抗它
I'm wondering if I can sign up to be part of the Borg, and fight it directly.
这辆太牛逼了
That is a cracker!
你看啊
Look at that.
配色不错
That's nice.
多惬意 胳膊伸在外面
He's cruising, arm out the window.
这虽然不是茶 但也挺好喝的
That isn't tea, but it is quite nice,
就连你都会说好喝
and even you will say it's quite nice.
里面可能有一些茶
It might have some tea in it.
-我宁愿喝杯啤酒 -你什么
-I'd rather have a beer. -You what?
我宁愿喝杯啤酒
I'd rather have a beer.
说到这件事 我知道...
Now on that front... I know
世界上所有首都里都有一家连锁的酒类专卖店
of a chain of off-licences to be found in every single capital city in the world,
即便在这样一个禁酒的穆斯林国家
and even in a dry country, a Muslim country like this one, which is very dry,
这样严格禁酒的国家 也能喝到金汤力
you could always get a gin and tonic
或者一杯清爽的啤酒
or a refreshing pint of beer.
-在这里是吗 店名是什么 -是的 很多地方都有
-An off-licence here. What's it called? -It's everywhere.
叫英国大使馆
It's called the British Embassy.
是吗
Ah! Is it?
大使馆是英国的主权领土
That is sovereign British territory.
-对 -所以我们能...
-Yes. -So we can...
他们一定会热烈欢迎我们 你这身可能差点意思
They're bound to welcome us, perhaps less so you,
然后我们就可以喝到酒了
and then we can have a refreshing drink.
-大使馆在哪儿 -喝完茶再走
-Where is it? -Finish your tea.
我不想喝
I don't want it.
在哈蒙德的坚持下 我找到了大使馆的电话号码
At Hammond's insistence, I found the number for the embassy,
预约成功 然后立即前往大使馆
got us an appointment, and we headed over there... immediately.
这就是这份工作中我最喜欢的部分
This is my favourite part of this job,
来到这样的一座城市
getting to a town like this...
四周充满了各种市井的声音
Just the buzz you get from a town like this.
我了个老天爷啊
Gordon Bennett!
哈蒙德出事故了
Hammond's had an accident.
他撞了我的阿斯顿
He's just rammed my Aston.
不会吧 有人撞上了他"崭新的"DB9
Oh no, someone's driven into his pristine DB9.
开车小心点 哈蒙德
You should drive more carefully, Hammond.
不赖我 他直接挤过去了
It wasn't me! He just went through.
好了各位 我找到了全场最佳
OK, we have a winner. Ladies and gentlemen, we have a winner.
我根本看不出来这是什么车
I have no idea what it is, or was.
我是真的看不出来
Well, I actually genuinely don't know what that was.
毫无头绪 看起来有点像旅行车
Not a clue, but it's a bit of estate car.
我觉得这个游戏可以到此为止了
I think that's the end of our car spotting here,
没人能击败这辆车
because you simply cannot beat that.
安全行驶了几公里之后 我们到达了英国大使馆
After a few crash-free miles, we arrived at the British Embassy.
就是这里了 伙计们 这是我们的俱乐部
It's here, chaps. Here is our club.
怎么称呼他们 "尊敬的大使"还是什么
Do you address them as Your Ambassadorship, or something like that?
"至高无上的您"
Yes, your Supreme-beingship.
还是直接叫"地主"吧
Or how about just 'landlord'?
金酒
Gin!
听我说
Anyway, listen, listen.
我觉得最有礼貌的方式是 有人问你"您要喝一杯吗"
I find it polite when somebody says "Can I offer you a drink," you say, no,
你说"不用了" 他们会追问"您确定吗"
and then they're, "Are you sure," and you go, "Well..."
你说"确定 不喝了" 然后你看一眼手表 说
And you look at your watch, and go,
"好吧 那就喝这一杯"
"Well, all right, just the one."
不能直接说"我喝"
But you don't say yes straight away.
不要"您喝金汤力吗" "喝" 别这样
Because, "Would you like a gin and tonic?" "Yes!" Don't do that.
-这样才有礼貌 -对 没错
-Yeah, I think it's polite, -yes, yes, yeah.
我脑子里只有金酒
I can only think about gin.
访客簿
这环境也太好了吧
Ooh that's very nice. Ooh isn't that very nice.
只有英国人会这样做
Only the British do this.
还有草坪 竟然有草坪
There's a lawn. That's a lawn.
那里有个吧台 但别往那边看
There's a bar, but don't look at it.
-你们好 -早上好
-Hey! -Good morning.
早上好 你们好吗 我是科林韦尔斯
Good morning. How are you? Colin Wells.
很高兴见到你们
It's very nice to meet you.
-你们看上去不错 -啊对对对
-You're looking very smart. -Oh yes.
他和终结者搏斗了一整晚 所以衣服有点脏
He spent all night fighting the Terminator. Hence the shirt.
我赢了
Successfully.
-请进 -谢谢
-Please go inside. -Thank you.
-最近怎么样 -还不错
How's it been going? Pretty good actually,
我是指我们俩
for us two.
最初发现要来毛里塔尼亚的时候 我们都很困惑
Um, we were slightly confused when we found we were coming to Mauritania,
虽然我们经常四处旅行
cos while we're quite well travelled,
但我们都...其实是他以为这地方不存在
we all look, all of us... Well, he didn't think it existed at all.
他以为是C.S.刘易斯书中的世界
He thought it was a C.S. Lewis invention.
但是当您被任命为大使时 您是怎么想的
But what did you feel like, when you got the posting?
我当时很高兴
Oh very happy.
-我想来 -您想来吗
-I wanted to come here. -You wanted to?
我一直想来这里
I wanted to come here.
您事前知道这是哪里
You knew where it was.
是的 我说我要去毛里塔尼亚 很多人都误以为
I did know where it was, and a lot of people in my life thought I was going to Mauritius
-我要去毛里求斯 -对就是这种情况
-when I told them I was going to Mauritania. -Exactly.
太棒了 我被分到了毛里求斯...塔尼亚
"Yes, I've got Mauritius." Mauritania?
噢对了 抱歉我忘了给你们拿点喝的
I'm sorry, I should offer you a drink. I'm really sorry. Um...
我喝
Yes please.
你们想喝点什么吗 我们这里有各种各样的茶
Would you like a drink? We've got um...a good range of teas here,
如果...你们觉得喝茶可以吗
if that would be uh-Would that sound all right to you?
-我有英式早餐茶 锡兰 -那个...
-I've got English Breakfast, Ceylon. -No, um...
-可以喝茶 -嗯 茶就行
-Tea, yes. -Yeah, lovely.
那我去点一壶
I'll just go and order one of those.
-失陪一下 -谢谢 您太热情了
-Just excuse me just for a moment. -Thank you. That's very hospitable.
骗子
You lied.
-现在怎么办 -都怪你
-Now look what's happened. -It's your fault.
-为什么怪我 -是你没处理好
-Why is it my fault? -You mishandled it.
可我们在英国 要讲礼貌
This is British territory.
我们确认过他这里真的有酒吗
Did we check that he does drink?
当然作为大使 不喝酒是不太可能的
I mean it's unlikely that an ambassador wouldn't drink but...
你看他那样子
Have you seen him?
显然不是个只喝碳酸饮料的人
That's not a man who's drank tonic water all his life.
如果我们刚才直说
If we'd immediately said,
"茶是不错 但您有没有更烈一点"
Actually that would be lovely but could I have a drink drink?
我承认我的礼貌让我们陷入了一点小麻烦
I will agree. My good manners have got us into a spot of bother here.
是的
Yes.
现在没外人 我想问问你
Can I ask whilst we're alone,
作为捷豹车主 你准备把哪幅画偷走
as you're a Jag driver, which painting are you going home with?
这些画都非常棒
Cos there's some very nice ones.
-你要去哪里 -伙计们
-Where are you going? -Oh, chaps.
我搞砸了
I've ballsed this up completely.
这是他的费列罗巧克力
It's his "Ferraro Roche".
-你个笨手笨脚的大猩猩 -啊这...
-You daft sod! -OK, that is...
这可不是大使行为...
That's not very ambass-
这些人都受过良好的教育
These people are trained to be suave.
他们风度翩翩 温文尔雅 而你这个笨蛋
They're smart, and cool, and you've knocked over
却弄倒了他们的费列罗巧克力塔
their tower of Ferrero Roche, you cretin!
快点照原样摆回去
Put those back on in the right order.
-抱歉我不应该笑 -那颗被你踩了
-Sorry, I shouldn't be laughing. -You've trodden on that one.
-不是我 -那就是别人
-I haven't trodden on it. -Somebody has.
快点坐好
Right, quickly, sit down.
-抱歉久等了 -我刚要说
-Oh, sorry to be slow. -Oh, I say.
这个壶很精致啊
That's a rather fine pot.
是的 这是我们的官方瓷器
Yeah, that's our official crockery.
这正是我想要的 一杯茶
That's exactly what I wanted, a cup of tea,
-令人神清气爽对吧 -确实是
-it's very refreshing, isn't it? -It is.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
礼貌地喝过一两壶之后
After a polite pot or two,
我们找了个借口离开 继续游览这座城市
we made our excuses and were able to resume our tour of the city.
我们再换一次档吧 再来一次
Let's have another gear change. Come on, let's do it again.
再来一次 给点力
Let's do it again. Come on.
喔 感觉真美妙
Aww, another gear change.
很快 我们就发现了一件有趣的事情
Soon, we came across something rather intriguing.
这里是怎么回事
What is going on here?
这条路也太宽了
It's a very wide road.
我知道这是为什么
I know what this is.
是什么
What?
他们原先在城市旁边建了一座机场
They built an airport right next to the city,
后来城市不断扩张 淹没了机场
and then the city grew, and sort of swamped the airport.
在市区里留下了一条飞机跑道
And they've been left with a runway right in the middle of the capital city.
-还真是 你看城市在继续向那边扩张 -是的
Oh yes, cos look, there's more city over there, so it's... -Yeah.
我们就在市区里
It's not on the edge. It's in it.
这难道不是一个绝佳的机会吗
Is this not an excellent opportunity
可以做一些刚才没做成的事情 也就是直线加速赛
for something we failed to do the other day, i.e. a drag race?
-对啊 -跑道就是用来跑直线加速赛的
-Oooh yes! -Runways are indeed for drag races.
-而且他... -他的车已经修好了
-And he... -And he's mended.
你也可以参加
You can take part.
我还没完全和我车内的邪恶势力交涉成功
I haven't raised it with the forces of evil in there yet,
但我很想参与一下
but I'd love to have a go.
鉴于这条路跟其他废弃的机场跑道一样 空无一人
Since the runway was as empty as any other abandoned airstrip,
于是我们决定开始比赛
we decided we were good to go.
切换到运动模式 关闭牵引力控制系统
Right, sport, traction control off,
拨片换挡 戴上墨镜 升起车窗 准备就绪
use the paddles, sunglasses down, windows up, ready.
不让我选择运动模式
It's taken sport mode away.
我的车不想让我使用运动模式
You know my sport button? It's decided I can't have it.
噢这回可以了 谢谢您 主人
Oh no, I can again. Thank you... Master.
V6 V8 V12
V6, V8, V12.
究竟谁会获胜
Which would be quickest?
捷豹的起步非常不错
A good start from the Jag.
我的车真快
Oh! My car is fast!
升档 再升一档 太好了 变速箱在正常工作
One gear, two gears. Brilliant! It's working!
稍等
Hang on a minute.
路上怎么有车
That is... that's traffic.
跑道上有车 妈的 我要...
The runway has traffic. Holy shit, I'm gonna have a...
怎么开的
Maniac!
天啊 怎么回事
Jeez, what the...
糟糕
Shit!
我的天啊
Oh dear God!
我刚才差点就撞上了
Oh, that's a-that's a-I was going to hit that...
老天爷啊
Holy moly!
这是我参加过的最奇怪的直线加速赛
That was the weirdest drag race I've ever done.
这并不是废弃跑道对吗
This is not an empty runway, is it?
我觉得当地人可能已经把这里当成一条路了
I don't think it's a runway anymore. I think it might be a road.
我们别再这样玩命了
Let's not do that again.
谢谢您能在我需要的时候给我刹车
Thank you for giving me the brakes when I needed them.
感恩的心 感谢有你
I'm very grateful and I appreciate it. Thank you.
第二天早上 我们起了个大早
The next morning, we were up bright and early,
因为是时候离开努瓦克肖特了
because it was time to leave Nouakchott.
这些卡车装满了沙子 他们要把沙子卖给谁
These lorries full of sand, who are they going to sell it to?
他们这的沙子品质真不错
They've got some lovely sand for sale over here.
这里可多了
There are big piles of it here.
如果你不喜欢刚才那堆 那还有
In case you didn't like the sand earlier, there's some sand there.
沙子的市场竞争真激烈
Very competitive market, sand.
他们为什么要卖沙子
Why do they sell sand?
每走十米就能看到沙子
You can literally walk 30 feet.
毛里塔尼亚
努瓦克肖特
然后我们离开了首都 向南前往塞内加尔
We then left the capital, heading south for Senegal.
达喀尔
塞内加尔
几个小时后 我们开始注意到周围环境的变化
And after a few hours, we started to notice a change in our surroundings.
这虽算不上绿洲
I wouldn't call it lush,
但我们之前见过的地方都比这贫瘠
but it's less barren than anything we've seen so far, that's for sure.
我觉得 这里已经非常接近撒哈拉沙漠的边缘了
I think we're very close to the edge of the Sahara Desert here.
右边那是什么 牛吗
What are they on the right? Are they cows?
应该说是一群牛 肯定是有人放牧的
Many cows. It's a herd. That's definitely been farmed.
快看
Look at it.
这说明 我们已经穿过撒哈拉沙漠了
And that tells me that we have crossed the Sahara.
你们好哇牛牛 让我瞅瞅
Hello, cows. Look at you!
草地 我感觉有500年没开过草地了
Grass. I'm driving on grass for the first time in what feels like 500 years.
我们正在找塞内加尔的边境入口
What we're looking for is a border into Senegal.
那应该会有检查站之类的 然后就能入境了
So there'll be, like, you know, a checkpoint. And in we go
我们沿着无数条路越走越远
We drove further and further along the myriad of tracks,
但一个小时后
but even after an hour,
我们还没看到边境入口的影子
we still hadn't found anything that looked remotely official.
这该死的边境在哪
Where's this bloody border?
我本以为会有围栏和检查站之类的
I was expecting, like, a fence and a checkpoint, maybe.
是的 然后就是查验护照等程序
Yeah, a passport and so on. Yeah, definitely.
终于 我们的搜寻有了结果
Finally, our search seemed to bear fruit.
这肯定是个边陲小镇 必须是
This has to be a border town. It has to be.
不好
Oh, no.
我有一种不详的预感
I've got a horrible feeling.
休斯顿
Houston,
我们遇到麻烦了
we have a problem.
我怀疑那就是边境
That, I suspect, is the border.
请问 这是塞内加尔吗
Excusez-moi. C'est Sénégal, là?
这是塞内加尔还是毛里塔尼亚
Sénégal. C'est Mauritanie? Sénégal ?
没错 那是塞内加尔
Senegal, right.
杰里米 我们面前有条巨大的河
Jeremy, there's a huge river in the way.
这边境的含“河”量比我预想的高
The border is a bit more rivery than I thought it was going to be.
-我原以为会有围栏 -我也是
-I thought fence. -I did.
没事 那有桥
That's all right. There's a bridge.
我拿手机查查
I'll get my phone out.
你怎么查 “我附近的桥”吗
What are you entering? "Bridges near me"?
这有条路
There's a road.
我们是最出色的探险家
We're the best explorers.
这有座老城
An old town there.
-没有桥 -没有桥
-No bridge. -No bridge.
天啊 你们是怎么...
Oh shit. How do you get to...
所以从没人开车去那吗
So nobody ever goes there in a car?
没错
No.
好吧 我沿着上游看了160多公里 都没有桥
OK, look, I've gone about a hundred miles down... upstream, and there's no bridge.
这就是为什么人们将河流视作边境
This is precisely why people use rivers as borders.
我们能把车放在... 不行
Could we get the cars on... No.
那上面吗
On that?
我想的是两艘那样的船 这也太...
Two of those boats, I was thinking about. It's a bit...
但这船... 等等
But boats that... Hang on...
如果我们自己造一艘船呢
What if we built a boat?
-用灰尘或者沙子吗 -咱也不是造方舟啊
-Out of dust, or sand? -I don't mean an ark.
我是指... 那种....
I just mean, like, a... What about...
我们手边有总重近六吨的三辆车
What have we got here? Two, four, six... Nearly six tons of car.
也不是非得造艘船 平台也行
It doesn't really need to be a boat. It just needs to be a platform.
你们看着附近 什么很多
What do you see a hell of a lot of here?
随处可见
Just anywhere you stand?
来这之后 我看到了什么
What have I seen since I got here? Dust.
-灰尘 -沙子
-Dust. -Sand.
-山羊 -骆驼
-Goats. -Camels.
没错
That's it.
-还有一样 -这就有沙子和骆驼
-And one other thing. -There's sand, there's camels.
数量庞大
...in vast numbers.
-塑料瓶 -是的
-Plastic bottles. -Yes.
-压扁的塑料瓶 -是的 但是够多啊
-Yes. -Flattened plastic bottle. Yes, but plenty.
我们刚刚开车压扁的 如果我们能找到
We've just driven over that one. What if we find-Well, find,
-1,2... -应该是说收集到足够多的塑料瓶
-Yeah, one, two... -just gather as many plastic bottles as we can.
-...3, 4... -这哪哪都是啊
-...3, 4. -There's one over there. Over there. They're everywhere.
-这主意不错 -我们就能建个...
-It's a good point. -And we build...
如果我们能有... 他们用什么做...看 渔网
If we could get-What do they do with-Look, nets.
-你是说我们搞张渔网 -是的
-You're suggesting we get a fishing net. -Yes.
-里边装满塑料瓶 -是的
-Fill it with plastic bottles. -Yes.
-我相信这肯定会浮起来 -是的
-I agree that would float. -Yes.
-然后把车放上去 -是的
-Then we put a car on it. -Yes.
我觉得这就浮不起来了
I don't agree that would float.
-如果瓶子足够 可以的 -没错
-It will if you have enough bottles. -Exactly.
-这就是物理中的浮力 -浮力不像情人 它安全且可控
It's buoyancy. It's just physics.It's not a cruel and unpredictable mistress.
-是的 这就和土地一样 -什么
-No, it isn't. It's much like ground. -What isn't?
-当然危险了 -浮力就是阿基米德原理 已经提出...
-Of course it is. -It's Archimedes. It's been understood for...
如果浮力\安全可控 怎么还会有人溺水
Nobody would drown if it wasn't cruel and unpredictable.
-这原理是古时候流传下来的 -是的
-It's been known since antiquity... -Yes.
而且从未被证伪
And the rules still work.
而且 我们也是在保护环境
Also, we are tidying up.
-这我同意 -没毛病
-That I agree with. -That's true. Yes.
我们离开时可以还它一片净土
We're leaving the place better than we found it.
既然如此 我们是否应该放背景音乐了
On that basis, then, shall we cue the music?
奏乐
Cue the music.
这应该大有用处
That could be very useful.
完美
Perfect.
我得躺会
I need a lie-down.
别过来 好吗 说了我对你不感兴趣
No, all right? Just no. I'm not interested.
太爽了
Oh. Oh, yes.
在花了好几万买天龙特工队音乐的使用版权后
Having spent thousands of pounds on a license to use all that A-Team music,
我们终于做出了木筏
our raft was finally completed.
为了测试它的可行性
And to see whether it worked,
我们决定先用备用车试试水
we decided to send the backup van first.
-我们吸引了一大群人 -是的
-We've drawed a crowd. -Yes.
他们觉得我们会沉水里去 我也是
Expecting us all to drown, which we will.
-那他们要失望了 -我们肯定会沉的
- We won't. They'll be disappointed. -We will. We will.
-克拉克森 -怎么了
What?
-笔直往后 我另一侧可以吗 -安全 笔直往后
-Straight back. Am I good that side? -Yeah, straight back.
-好了 -这是我的主意 对吧
Right. Now, um, this is my idea, yeah?
-是的 -所以这次我掌舵
-Yes. -So I'm the captain. This time.
现在分工 三人各司其职
Uh, jobs. There are three.
我就在车上 到对岸之后把车开上岸
I'm going to be with the van. So my job is drive it off at the other side.
詹姆斯 你负责前面
James, you're on the front.
到对岸后 你指挥我们安全上岸
When we get there, you've got to get us on the bank and safe.
好的
Right.
杰里米 你在后面操作马达
Jeremy, you're operating the motor at the back.
但是 丑话说在前面 我觉得这事成不了
But, I just want to make this absolutely clear, I don't believe this will work.
会成功的
Oh, it'll work.
不 听我说 我也真心不想乱来
Well, no, listen. Genuinely, genuinely, I don't want any cocking around,
因为这里有传染病 是一种寄生虫
'cause there's a disease. Well, it's a parasite. Um.
血吸虫病
Schistosomiasis.
我们可以把这打在屏幕下方 大家自行搜索
Uh, we can put that on the screen at the bottom and you can Google it.
到时候你们就知道我不是在胡说了
And you'll know I'm not making this up.
这塞内加尔河里就有这种寄生虫
In the Senegal River, which is this, OK? It's a parasite.
如果掉进河里 虫子就会吸附在你的皮肤上
If you go in the water, it will attach itself to your skin,
钻进你的身体 进入你的血液
burrow through your flesh, into your bloodstream,
然后进入你的肝脏和肠道 开始产卵
where it is carried to your liver and your intestines, where it lays its eggs.
别掉进河里 无论怎样 我们一鼓作气 冲过去
Don't jump in. Whatever happens, we'll chug across there.
只有这么远 你看 就在那儿
It's only there. Look, it's there.
启动马达
Firing up the motor.
英国皇家海军"屎亡号"启航
HMS Shit is-aargh!
迫不及待想看我们笑话的本地人
Eager to see some comedy capsizing,
热情地帮我们推船下水
the locals were happy to push us off.
-好了 -出发了
-Oh yes! -We're going.
感谢
Merci ! Merci !
到那之后 你得带我们转个向
I think if you can turn us when we get out there.
好的
OK.
称呼理查德哈蒙德为"船长" 感觉太奇怪了
That feels weird, calling Richard Hammond captain.
我之所以愿意听他指挥 是因为一旦出了岔子 我可不背锅
I shall do as he says, because when it goes wrong, it won't be my fault.
虽然速度很慢 但确实在前进
It's very slow, but it is going.
慢中有稳 正正合适
Slow and steady, that's all we need.
-别紧张 -只要转个向 我们就能提速了
Relax. Once we've got it turned, we'll make better headway.
早知道就带把椅子了
I should have brought a chair.
船头要转过去了
The front's coming round.
-船头... -糟糕
-The front is com... -Oh, shit!
-看看你能发动它吗 -好的 我来试试
-See if you can start it. -OK, trying the motor.
伙计们
Uh, chaps!
-我们的...不见了 -什么
-We've lost... -What!
没什么 别...别慌
Nothing. Don't... don't panic.
什么不见了
What have we lost?
这些该死的瓶子脱勾了
Um, we've lost some of the bloody... The bottles have come off.
-什么 -什么
-What? -What?
浮力瓶脱...我们不像在下沉 但我们真的正在下沉
The buoyancy bottles have com... No, that isn't like we're sinking. We actually are.
大伙尽量离那边远一些
Everybody stand on this side as far as you can.
-天啊 - 是谁栓的绳子
-Oh jesus! -Who lashed those on?
杰里米 船确实在下沉
Uh, Jeremy, it really is actually sinking.
-马达启动了 -太好了 回岸边
-Motor is on! -Excellent. Head for shore.
伙计们 我会尽力把我们送回岸边
Right, I'm going to try and get us back, chaps.
好吧 你说得对 我们得吸取教训
OK, I think you're right. Let's-We'll learn from this.
-另一侧状态怎样 -有点下沉
How's it looking at the other side? It's looking a bit sinky.
我觉得我们应该没问题
I think, we should be all right, I think.
-又熄火了 -天啊
-It's gone again! -Oh, Jesus.
-这是要沉... -沉得越来越快了
Is that going down It's going down much more quickly.
别别别 不要啊
Oh, no, no, no, no, no, no, no!
我觉得是时候跳船逃生了
I think probably abandon ship.
我需要...能给我个水桶吗
Can you pass me a water bottle?
-詹姆斯 -给我一个水桶
-James! -Pass me a water bottle.
这不行
That's not worked.
-不 我不相信 -我才是船长 去你的
-No, I don't believe it. -I'm the captain. Bugger this.
-哈蒙德 你可是船长啊 -抱歉
-Hammond you're the captain. -I'm sorry!
谢谢 我没...我还在船上
Thank you. I'm not-I'm still on.
詹姆斯 船要沉了 你得跳下来
James, it's going to go all the way over. You'll have to go off.
救命 虫子正在朝我体内钻呢
Burrowing. They're burrowing into me.
我j就是下一个约翰赫特
I'm John Hurt.
船沉了...天啊
It has sunk comp-Oh, God!
-沉了吗 -沉了
-Is it gone? -It's gone.
沉了
It's gone.
我没事
I'm all right!
-你可以从那走过来 -你都能走上来了
-You can walk from there. -You can walk from there.
话别说太早
Well, you say that...
往前走 别停 不然你会陷进泥潭 那就要命了
But keep your feet moving or you sink into the mud and it kills.
-这都是屎? -没错
-Is this faeces?  -Yeah, it is all faeces.
我已经吸入了
And I have injested a lot of it.
-一大口吗 -很多
-A lot of it? -a lot of it.
-好吧 -你只能听天由命了
-OK. -You're on your own.
你得来些抗生素了
You're gonna need some antibiotics.
一大管子
A big needle full.
我有话要说
Um, can I just point something else out?
我们的货车牺牲了
We've lost our van.
这确实不妙 但是
OK, that is bad, but...
我们已经有足够的材料为三辆车造木筏了
we've already harvested enough materials to build rafts for the cars.
所以 还没彻底完蛋
So we're not out yet.
-他在胡说什么 -刚才的那番努力虽有瑕疵
-What's he on about? -Well, there are flaws with that particular effort, yes.
但我们可以 也应该做更好
We know we can do better and shall.
所以 等你上岸把自己晾干
So as soon as you're out and all dried, there's only one thing to do.
只需要做一件事
There's only one thing to do.
不 该奏乐了
No. It's cue the music.
什么
What?
-我们还得过河 -我们还在这头呢
-We've still got to get across. -We're not over there, are we?
我知道你现在不好受
I know you feel rough.
-是的 -我知道你63岁了
-I do. I know you're 63
-而且寄生虫已经深入内脏 -是的 进肝了
-and you're full of beetles burrowing their way out of your organs. -Yes. Into my liver.
而且接下来一周 你还要经历慢性腹泻
And you're going to have chronic diarrhoea for the next week.
-但是对岸有一个酒吧 -好的
-Yes. -But over there is a bar.
-这里可没有 -好的
-Yes. -Over here there isn't. Yes.
-要是我们去那边 就能坐进酒吧 -好的
-We go over there. -Yes. -We're in the bar.
-所以 我们该切背景音了 -没错 -切吧
-So we're saying cue the music.-Yeah. -Cue the music.
第二天我们准备好了 过境方案2.0
The next day, we were ready for border crossing 2.0.
我承认 情况有点错综复杂
Um, we've faced some complexities, I admit.
因为很显然 要保证车头不进水
Because you've got to keep the front of the car out of the water, obviously.
但与此同时 必须让后轮刚好入水
But you've got to have the back wheels just in the water
因为我们在后轮上安装了桨叶 功能类似轮桨
because we've attached paddles to them, like propellers,
这将提供向前或向后的动力
which will give us forward movement or reverse movement.
至于操舵
Steering?
这里有...一副舵
Well, there's a rudder here
它通过后视镜那边的连杆相连
which is attached to a sort of lever by the door mirror there.
肯定不好使
And that won't work.
他俩认为会管用 但我不觉得
James and Richard think it will. I think it won't.
这太棒了
This is brilliant.
詹姆斯 你觉得会成功吗
James, do you think this is going to work?
詹姆斯 你觉得会成功吗 杰里米在问你
James, do you think this is going to work? Jeremy's asking you.
-詹姆斯梅 -怎么了
-James May? -What?
你觉得会成功吗
Do you think this is going to work?
什么
What?
他太老了
He's so old.
你觉得会成功吗
Do you think... this... is going to... work?
当然了
Yes.
好了 我要试试 挂上档
Right, um, I'm going to give it a go. Going into gear.
当地人渴望看到我们重蹈昨日的覆辙
Keen to see a repeat of yesterday's calamity,
于是更加热情地把我们推进了河
the locals were even more eager to help get us going.
谢谢
Merci.
-多谢各位 -你们真好
Merci, monsieur. Merci, merci, très gentil.
谢谢
Merci.
正在操舵
Rudder deploying.
蠢货 别碰方向盘 根本没用啊
Oh, don't touch the steering wheel, you idiot. It doesn't do anything.
你好
Hello!
理查德哈蒙德 我看到你和DB9在...
What I'm seeing, Richard Hammond, is you and the DB9 on a...
别胡来 你这个自私鬼
No, don't do that, you selfish man.
我们在塞内加尔一侧的登陆点
Our landing point on the Senegalese side
是一个相距仅400米的小海滩
was a small beach just 400 metres away.
好了 我要在对岸来个完美漂移
Right. So, now I'm going to execute a perfect curving turn.
开上去 出示护照 进入塞内加尔 啤酒整起来
Up onto the landing beach, drive up, show my passport, Senegal, beer.
然而 我们很快发现这一次 杰里米居然说对了
However, we soon discovered that for once, Jeremy had been right.
转向失效
The steering didn't work.
我不能左转 只能往右
I can't turn left. I can only go right.
即便我打满右舵 还是向左
I turn left even with full right rudder.
不能...我的船舵不往右转 只能向左
It won't-Mine won't turn right. I can only go left.
女士们先生们 我很想告诉大家
I'd love to be able to explain, ladies and gentlemen
我即将抵达彼岸 但并没有
I'm arriving at the other side, but I'm not.
我又回到了出发的地方
I'm arriving back where I started from.
给点力啊 你个混蛋
Come on, you bastard.
救命 我开进芦苇丛了
Oh, I'm in the reeds.
求救 混蛋
Mayday. Bollocks.
后退三
Full reverse.
不要 你...
Oh! No, you...
我们造的是脚踏船 对吧
We've built pedalos, haven't we?
对 但后船标是著名的汽车品牌
Yeah, but with great brand names on the back.
接下来的一个小时 我们四处航行 哪都去过了
For the next hour, we sailed around, managing to go everywhere,
唯独到不了心心念的彼岸
except the beach we were headed for.
我正在朝错误的方向横向漂移 就是这么个情况
I'm drifting sideways in the wrong direction, is what I'm doing.
我做出了两次超大的U形掉头
What I've done is two enormous U-turns.
当地人以为我们疯了
The locals think we're deranged.
它把我又带回毛里塔尼亚了
It's taking me back to Mauritania.
我不想回去
I don't want to go back to Mauritania.
有人能告诉我那边有什么吗 我正往那去
Can anybody tell me what's down here, because that's where I'm going.
是大海
The sea.
我完全卡在角落里了 两侧都是墙
I'm completely stuck in a corner with walls on two sides of me.
转啊 你个混蛋
Turn, you bastard, turn.
我欣赏她淡定洗衣服的样子 好像这种喜剧每天都会发生
I love the way she's just doing her washing, as though this happens every single day.
该死 不好了
Oh, bloody hell, no. Oh no.
我的天啊
Oh, my God.
别再撞我了
Stop crashing into me!
我又回到芦苇丛了
I'm back in the reeds!
刚才有人驶向过正确方向吗 哪怕只有一会
Has anybody managed to go the right way at any point?
没有
No.
再次挣脱芦苇之后
Having freed myself from the reeds again,
我有一项关于舵的重大发现
I made an important steering-related discovery.
如果龟速前进 我是说 空档蠕动
If you go incredibly slowly, I mean, tick over, OK,
就可以向右了 一旦提速 就会变成向左转
you can turn right. If you increase speed, you go left.
随着所有人应用了我的新发现
With all of us deploying my new discovery,
我们很快就朝着正确的方向前进
we were soon heading in the right direction.
太棒了
Oh, yes!
我要成功了 正在驶向对岸
I am going to do it. I am heading for the shore.
走起来
Drive, drive!
我闻到啤酒味了
I can smell beer!
聪明如我 明白靠岸需要大量的动力
Being intelligent, I knew I'd need a big burst of power to get ashore.
于是 我升起车顶 保护脑子免受寄生虫的侵害
So I raised my roof to protect my head from the parasites.
真不错啊
Well done.
我快到了
I'm so nearly there!
求你了 就这一次 往左吧
Please, just for once, go left.
我靠岸了
Oh, I've hit the bank.
我们的前轮进入了塞内加尔 这算吗
Our front wheels are in Senegal, does that count?
我觉得肯定开到了塞内加尔 是的 我们到了
Oh, I think we're definitely in Senegal, yeah, I think we've arrived.
显然 将这三辆车改回去 我们还有工作要做
Obviously, there is work to be done returning these to be normal land-based vehicles,
但有一些更重要的事 我们需要优先处理
but there's something more important to attend to first.
你们俩跟我不一样
You two are different to me.
我看着这杯啤酒 会想
I look at that and I just think,
"多么伟大的发明!"
"Oh, what an invention!"
看着它 品味它
Now, looking at it, savouring it,
就像喝它一样令人愉悦
is as enjoyable as drinking it.
看看杯子上凝结的水珠 看看翻腾的气泡
Look at the condensation on the glass, look at the bubbles,
看看...品味一下这种期待
look at the... Savour the anticipation.
因为在我看来 这也一样美
Because in my mind, it's as good.
视觉上 这体验很好 但听觉上太烦了
Visually, this is a good experience. Aurally, it's annoying.
-很烦吗
It's annoying?
-我看到了尤物 听到了胡话
I'm just seeing beauty, hearing bollocks.
显然 我们决定多喝几杯
Obviously, we decided to have more than one.
自然 随着哈蒙德开始喝上下一轮
So, as Hammond was getting the next round in,
我溜到他的车上 搞了一点终结者风格的恶作剧
I slipped out to his car for a bit of Terminator-based mischief.
如果把我的手机 蓝牙连接到这台扬声器
If I Bluetooth my phone to this speaker
然后把它藏在哈蒙德的车上
and hide that in Hammond's car,
我就可以给他播放消息
I can play messages to him
他会以为车在对话
and he'll think his car is talking to him.
第二天早上 我们重新汇合 继续旅程
The next morning, we reconvened to continue our journey.
好了
Right.
模仿了终结者T-800的口音
下车 滚下车
Get out. Get out.
怎么回事
-What the hell was that?
我的车刚刚让我滚下去
My car just told me to get out.
-不会吧 -它让我下车
-No. -It told me to get out.
如果我是那辆车 我也会赶的 但是...
I must admit, I'd tell you to get out if I was that car, but...
下车
-Get out.
-听到了吗 -确实
-Do you hear that? -I did hear that.
太诡异了 不是吗
Well, that is weird, isn't it?
-那天晚上你是不接入电脑了 -是的
Were you in its computer the other night? -Yes.
-那就是问题所在 -我与它深入对接了
-That's what's gone wrong. -I was deeply intimate with it.
总之 继续走吧
Anyway, forwards.
我就知道
I knew it!
幼稚
Child.
你们好
Hello, hello. Bonjour. Bonjour.
塞内加尔 多么热烈的欢迎
Senegal. Helluva welcome.
现在 我们距离达喀尔的终点线 只剩下了几百公里的坦途
We were now just a couple of hundred easy miles to the finish line in Dakar.
圣路易斯
达喀尔
在我们史诗般的旅程即将结束之际
And with our epic trip this close to the end,
这似乎是一个很好的时机 让我们点评一下
it seemed like a good time to reflect on the machines
带我们来的三台机器
that had brought us here.
节目开始时 我们提出问题
We asked at the beginning of this show
有没有可能花费低于兰博基尼飓风Sterrato版的价钱
if it would be possible to build a rally-raid Dakar desert racer car
制造一辆达喀尔沙漠拉力赛车
for less than a Lamborghini Huracán Sterrato.
答案是肯定的
And the answer is yes.
妥妥的
Yes.
我被这辆车惊呆了 彻底惊呆了
I'm staggered by this car. Absolutely staggered,
因为它爬过了岩石峭壁
'cause it's clawed its way up rocky escarpments,
跨过了江海河流 疾驰于沙丘之间
it's been across rivers, it's blasted across dunes.
与那辆"鬼上身"的阿斯顿马丁不同
And unlike the Aston, which is possessed by the devil,
更与几乎散架的玛莎拉蒂 形成鲜明对比
and the Maserati, which, under the skin, is falling to pieces,
这辆车没出任何差错
this has not put a single foot wrong.
我们之前每次冒险时驾驶过的车辆 我都非常喜爱
I've been fond of cars we've used on these adventures in the past,
但都不及我对这辆车的喜爱
but nothing like as fond as I am of this.
等我开到达喀尔之后 我会非常想它的
I'm going to miss it badly when I get to Dakar.
真的 真的会想念它
Really, really miss it.
如果我在节目开始就说 我要改装一辆
Now, if I'd said to you at the beginning "I'm going to take "an exotic car
小批量生产的意大利豪华车
" from a small-volume Italian manufacturer and I'm going to modify it
还要驾驶它穿越沙漠
and I'm going to drive it across the desert,"
你可能会说 "不 你诓我"
you'd have probably said, "No, you're not."
但我们做到了 就在此刻
But here we are. It's here!
我们正驶向达喀尔
On the way to Dakar,
也就是世界上 最激动人心 最艰难比赛的终点
the finishing point for the most dramatic and gruelling race in the world.
而且别忘了 截至目前 我的车是三辆车中最好看的
And let's not forget, mine is by far the best-looking of the three cars,
而且是唯一比原厂车外观更漂亮的
and mine is the only one that looks better now than it did when it was standard.
我真的改进了原版的外观
I've actually improved the original.
赢家
Winner!
也许你会觉得 我很难拿出令人信服的证据
Now, you might imagine I'd struggle to mount a convincing argument
证明把阿斯顿马丁DB9 Volante改装成拉力赛车的合理性 但慢着
I've improved my Aston Martin DB9 Volante by turning it into a rally racer, but hold on.
如果我没有改装 这辆车将会保持原样
If I hadn't done that, this car, left unchanged, would have simply...
继续在 彼得伯勒 混日子
continued living in Peterborough,
来回穿梭于郊区住宅
commuting between suburban home
和中等规模的工业区之间
and a middle-sized trading estate.
周末参加高尔夫俱乐部的奇怪旅行
With the odd trip out to the golf club at weekends.
它仍然会闪闪发亮 但会陷入宿命
It would have stayed shiny and nice, but it would have become what it is,
一辆略显过时 缓缓凋零
which is a slightly outdated, slowly fading example
曾经辉煌过的豪华跑车
of a once-grand grand tourer.
通过我的改装
By doing what I've done to it,
我能够将它带到这里 做一些了不起的事情
I've been able to bring it out here to do something incredible.
而这些经历如今都镌刻在车身上
And those experiences are now written across it
显示在划痕 擦痕 凹痕和裂缝之中
in scuffs and scrapes and dents and cracks.
这些是它的命脉 是它脸上的笑纹
They are its lifelines, its laughter-lines on it.
我很喜欢它
And I love it.
之前它并不特别 但现在 足够特别了
I made it special. It wasn't special. Now it is.
我们开到了极其美丽的圣路易斯  这座小城的海岸线上
We hit the coast in the surprisingly pretty town of St Louis
然后一路向南 与大西洋平行前进
and turned south, running parallel with the Atlantic Ocean.
这给我了灵感
Which gave me an idea.
我们为什么不像以前那样 从沙滩进入达喀尔
Why don't we go into Dakar on the beach, like they used to?
拉力赛的终点设置在沙滩上
On the rally? It was finished on the beach.
对啊
Yes!
当然 我的同事们没有任何异议
Naturally, my colleagues had no objections whatsoever.
所以 我们转头驶入沙滩 完成最后的112公里
So we turned onto the sand to complete the last 70 miles,
就像过去的赛车手一样
just as the races of the past had done.
机械增压启动
Supercharger engaged.
快看那边
Look at that!
巴黎达喀尔拉力赛 这就是终点
Paris-Dakar! This is the finish!
正是为了看到这特别的时刻
It will be for these exact moments that people
人们才会忍受巴黎达喀尔拉力赛 一路走来的苦难和艰辛
endured the suffering and hardship of doing the Paris-Dakar.
参赛就是为了这一刻
This is what they did it for. This!
我要和理查德"鼹鼠"哈蒙德 并肩前行
I'm going to pull alongside Richard "The Hamster" Hammond.
快看 我们开进海报了
Look at this! We're in a poster!
我谢谢您
Oh, thank you!
从来没有玩得这么开心过
Never had so much fun!
今天太美好了
What a wonderful, wonderful day.
有短信
Hello.
威尔曼先生发来的
Text message from Mr Wilman.
"进入达喀尔之前 你们可能想看一下新闻推送"
"Before going into Dakar, you might want to check your news feeds."
真的吗
Really?
英国广播公司新闻
BBC News.
气候变化 全是气候变化
Climate change, climate change, climate change.
洪水 气候变化
Floods, climate change.
试试推特
Try Twitter.
天啊
Oh, Christ.
等等 请回话 怎么停车了
Hang on. Coming. Why have you stopped?
怎么停车了
Why have you stopped?
威尔曼刚刚让我们看新闻
Wilman just said, "Check your news feeds."
这发生在达喀尔
That's Dakar.
什么
What?
达喀尔 发生了重大骚乱
Dakar. There's proper major riots.
已经开始了
It's kicked off.
天啊 骚乱的原因是什么
Oh, geez. What's that about?
谁知道 就是一些政治...我不知道
God knows. It's some political... I don't know.
-有很多... -这是...我知道...
-There's a lot of... -I know there's a lot, it's...
-有燃烧的公共汽车 应该... -天啊
-And it's burning buses. -Oh, God!
-你看这个了吗 -没有
-Have you seen this? -No.
达喀尔
Dakar.
骚乱已经开始了 还有枪战
It's properly kicked off. There are gun battles.
-还有火 有烧着的公共汽车 -是的
And there's fire. There's a bus on fire. Yeah.
好吧
Um... right.
这种情况不能带团队进去
You can't take the crew down there.
不能 谁都不应该... 我不想让任何人去
No, I know. Nobody sh-I don't want anyone going down there.
-我觉得不应该... -我之前知道有计划中的抗议行动
I mean, I knew there were some protests planned,
但应该是三四天之后
but that's about three or four days.
是为了抗议反对派 但显然提前开始了
It's over that opposition, but it's obviously kicked off early.
-但这是眼下发生的事 -也可能是别的原因 已经开始了
-That's now. -Or this is something else. Or it's getting ready to go,
这样的话情况会更恶劣
which means it's going to get worse.
等一下 我们的返程航班从达喀尔起飞
Wait a minute. Our flight home is from Dakar.
确实
It is.
-飞不成了 -不能飞了
-Well, we can't do that. -It's not an option.
-圣路易斯机场关闭了 -什么
-St Louis Airport's closed. -What?
-圣路易斯机场关闭了 -关闭了
-St Louis Airport's closed. -It's closed?
已关闭 正在整修 我刚查了
Closed. Refurbishment. Checked it.
这意味着 我们必须开车返回努瓦克肖特
That means we've got to drive back to Nouakchott.
-真的吗 这是唯一选择了? -反正我不去达喀尔
Seriously? Is that the only option? Well, I'm not going to Dakar.
来嘛 很有趣的
Come on, it'll be fun.
这就是一场往返式拉力赛了 这么着吧
It's a there and back rally. Right, then.
这倒表示了一件事
It does mean one thing.
-我可以用传统结束语了 -没错
-I can use the traditional ending. -Yes.
伴随着这糟糕的失望之情
On that terrible disappointment,
节目该结束了
it's time to end.
感谢大家的观看 下次再见
See you next time. Thanks for watching.
糟透了
F-ing hell.